<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE language SYSTEM "klayout_doc.dtd">

<doc>

  <title>The Main Window</title>
  <keyword name="Main window"/>

  <p>
  The main window is divided into three parts: the left area is the hierarchy browser and navigator, the 
  center part of the canvas and the right part is the layer list with the layer toolbox.
  The individual components can be rearranged, so the arrangement described is just the default
  arrangement. You can move a component to a new place by dragging it with its title bar to 
  some other place or detach it from the main window to form a floating separate window.
  </p>

  <p>
  <img src="/manual/main_window.png"/>
  </p>

  <h2>Left Part - The Hierarchy Browser, Library View and Navigator</h2>

  <p>
  The left panel is the
  hierarchy browser which shows the cell hierarchy and - optionally - the navigator window 
  that shows an overview over the whole layout.
  </p>

  <p>
  In the hierarchy browser, cell nodes can be
  expanded showing the child nodes. The "current cell" is the one shown in the center
  panel. It is drawn in bold font. One or multiple cells can be selected. The selected
  cells are the ones, the various functions act on. The "context cell" is the cell which
  is the "active cell" on which drawing happens. The context usually is the same than 
  the current cell, but by descending into the hierarchy, the child cell of the current
  cell can be made the context cell. It is shown in underlined font.
  </p>

  <p>
  In the following example, "TOPTOP_BIG" is selected, "TOPTOP" is the current cell and 
  "TOP" is the context cell:
  </p>

  <p>
  <img src="/manual/hierarchy_panel.png"/>
  </p>

  <p>
  The sub-panel below the hierarchy browser is the library view. This view
  shows the libraries registered in the system and their content:
  </p>

  <p>
  <img src="/manual/library_view.png"/>
  </p>

  <p>
  The library view is used to browse and place library cells, which can 
  be normal cells or PCells. Read more about the library view here: <link href="/manual/library_view.xml"/>.
  </p>

  <p>
  The navigator is invisible by default but can be activated by checking the 
  "Navigator" menu item in the "View" menu. The navigator shows an overview
  image of the whole cell and a box indicating the clip shown in the 
  center panel:
  </p>

  <p>
  <img src="/manual/navigator.png"/>
  </p>

  <h2>Center Part - The Canvas</h2>

  <p>
  The center panel is the actual canvas. There, the layout is drawn. To zoom 
  in, click with the right mouse button and drag a rectangle that will become 
  the new area shown. Select items by left-clicking or dragging a selection
  rectangle with the left mouse button pressed. A variety of edit and 
  display modification feature is supplied, for example the ability to 
  add rulers or background images.
  </p>

  <h2>Right Part - The Layer List and Layer Style Controls</h2>

  <p>
  The right panel is shows the layer list or layer tree. By default, it 
  shows a plain layer list, but the are manifold ways to configure the 
  list, i.e. grouping, styling, adding tabs to easily switch between 
  different setups etc.
  </p>

  <p>
  The layer tree specifies what and how layout is drawn. Entries can be 
  deleted or configured freely - this does not affect the layout itself. 
  Essentially, the layer list can be entirely independent from the layout
  and omit layers from the layout or add (empty) layers that are not 
  actually part of the layout. In this scenario, a layer list typically
  reflects a set of drawing layers with a certain technology-dependent
  meaning. This list provides a styled layer view for an otherwise
  undecorated layout file. The layers can be reordered, so their 
  drawing priority is changed. The top layer will be drawn first, 
  while others will be drawn later. Hence the first layer is likely
  to become obscured by following layers.
  </p>

  <p>
  Modification operators can be attached to layers - for example, the 
  drawn layout can be transformed geometrical (i.e. translated, rotated, 
  scaled, mirrored) and layout can be selectively drawn when certain 
  conditions for user properties apply.
  </p>

  <p>
  Below the layer list, a set of control panels is located. The control panels are
  minimized per default. They can be expanded by clicking on the header
  bar. These controls form the "Layer Toolbox" where you can modify the 
  layer styles. The styles selected in the layer toolbox will affect the 
  layers selected in the layer list.
  </p>

  <p>
  Multiple layouts can be shown together. Either they can be overlayed or
  they can be shown in separate views. In this case, a tab panel appears
  at top of the main window. Selecting a tab switches between the layouts.
  Layers for different layouts appear as annotated layers in the layer list - 
  for example "1/0@1" for layer 1, datatype 0, first layout and "1/0@2" for
  layer 1, datatype 0 and second layout.
  </p>

</doc>

