<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE language SYSTEM "klayout_doc.dtd">

<doc>

  <title>Doing Measurements</title>
  <keyword name="Rulers"/>

  <p>
  A measurement can be performed by clicking on the ruler icon in the 
  toolbar and selecting "Ruler" from the drop-down options.
  Left-click on a point in the layout and then left-click again to 
  specify the second point. A ruler will be shown that indicates
  the distance measured. 
  </p>

  <p>
  A more convenient way is provided with the single-click measurement
  ruler. Select "Measure" from the drop-down options of the ruler symbol.
  In this mode, a single click will set a ruler to the specified 
  position. This feature will look for edges in the vicinity of the 
  ruler and set the ruler to connect the neighboring edges. The ruler
  is attached perpendicular to the edge next to the initial point.
  </p>

  <p>
  Rulers can be configured in manifold ways. Use "Rulers And Annotations Setup" 
  in the "Edit" menu to open the ruler configuration dialog. 
  A ruler can be
  made to snap to edges of objects by selecting "Snap to edge/vertex".
  Ruler orientations can be constrained by using the "Angle Constraint"
  options. The number of rulers can be limited using the "Limit 
  number of annotations" setting.
  </p>

  <p>
  While drawing or moving one point of a ruler, the direction constraint
  can be overridden with the Shift and Ctrl keys: pressing Shift while moving the
  mouse will enforce orthogonal constraint, Ctrl will enforce diagonal constraint 
  while pressing both will release any direction constraint.
  </p>

  <p>
  All rulers can be cleared using the "Clear all rulers" function from the
  "Edit" menu.
  </p>

  <p>
  Ruler dragging can be canceled with the "Esc" key or using the "Cancel"
  function from the "Edit" menu.
  </p>

  <p>
  Rulers can be moved by selecting "Move" mode with the speedbar buttons
  in the toolbar or "Move" from the "Mode" submenu in the "Edit" menu. Then
  left-click and drag the ruler or the ruler end point that should be changed.
  </p>

  <p>
  Rulers can be deleted selectively by selecting a ruler in "Select" mode and
  pressing "Delete".
  </p>

  <p> 
  Rulers can be modified in a variety of ways. For example, rulers can be shown
  as arrows. To edit the properties of a ruler, double-click the ruler or 
  select it and use "Properties" from the "Edit" menu. 
  See <link href="/manual/ruler_properties.xml"/> for a description of the 
  properties.
  </p>

  <p> 
  Multiple templates can be configured to be available for rulers. Each template defined
  will be shown in the "Ruler" mode toolbar button's drop-down menu.
  If a template is selected, new rulers produced from this template will inherit
  the template's properties. Templates are managed in the 
  ruler setup page ("Setup" from the "File" menu) or "Ruler And Annotation Setup" from the "Edit" menu.
  </p>

</doc>

