<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE language SYSTEM "klayout_doc.dtd">

<doc>

  <title>Moving The Selection</title>
  <keyword name="Editing"/>
  <keyword name="Move"/>

  <p>
  The whole selection can be moved in "Move" mode. If some elements are already selected, choose "Move" mode and select 
  a reference point by left-clicking at the position. The reference point will be used as the "dragging handle" - each
  element is moved relative to this position. In no elements are selected when entering move mode, 
  simply click at the element to move and place it somewhere else with a left mouse click.
  </p>

  <p>
  While moving, the whole selection can be rotated by 90 degree counterclockwise with a right mouse 
  button click. 
  The Escape key will cancel the operation.
  </p>

  <p>
  For movements, the movement direction constraint apply. 
  See <link href="/manual/editor_options.xml"/> for details about the modes
  available. For example, in Manhattan mode, only horizontal and vertical movements are allowed.
  The global movement constraint can be overridden by pressing Shift (orthogonal), Ctrl (diagonal) or 
  both Shift and Ctrl (any angle) while moving the mouse.
  </p>

  <p>
  While you move the selection, two edit boxes are shown at the top of the layout view.
  Press the Tab key to enter these edit boxes.
  Use the Tab and Shift+Tab keys to navigate between the boxes.
  You can specify a numerical shift value here. Pressing the Enter key will apply these
  shifts. Pressing the Escape key will leave the edit fields.
  </p>

  <p>
  To apply a specific shift, you can also use "Move By" from the "Edit/Selection" menu.
  A dialog will open that allows specification of the horizontal and vertical move distance in micrometers.
  Positive values move to the top or right and negative ones to the bottom or left.
  This dialog also applies to partial mode, so that edges or parts of a layout can be 
  moved precisely by a certain distance in a certain direction.
  </p>

  <p>
  In the same way, "Move To" allows one to reposition the selection to a certain point. The point which
  is positioned can be chosen relative to the bounding box of the selection. If first example,
  the lower-left corner of the selection is picked as the reference point and a certain position
  is given in the dialog, the selection is moved such that the lower left position of its
  bounding box will match the given coordinate.
  </p>

</doc>

