<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE language SYSTEM "klayout_doc.dtd">

<doc>

  <title>LVS Netlist Tweaks</title>
  <keyword name="LVS"/>
  <keyword name="LVS Netlist Tweaks"/>

  <h2-index/>

  <p>
  Netlist tweaking is important to standardize netlists. Without tweaking,
  the extracted netlist may contain elements that are redundant or
  don't match anything found in the schematic.
  </p>

  <p>
  Netlist tweaks are applied on the extracted <class_doc href="Netlist"/> object. 
  This can be obtained with the <a href="/about/drc_ref_global.xml#netlist">netlist</a> function.
  This function will extract the netlist if not done already.
  </p>

  <p>
  Netlist tweaks can also be applied to the schematic netlist. For example to flatten away 
  a model subcircuit called "NMOS", use this <class_doc href="Netlist#flatten_circuit"/>:
  </p>

  <pre>schematic.flatten_circuit("NMOS")</pre>

  <h2>Top level pin generation</h2>

  <p>
  Circuits extracted don't have pins on the top hierarchy level as the
  extractor cannot figure out where to connect to this circuit.
  The compare function does not try to match pins in this case.
  But to gain a useful extracted netlists, pins are required.
  Without pins, a circuit can't be embedded in a testbench for 
  example. 
  </p>

  <p>
  KLayout offers a function to create top-level pins using 
  a simple heuristics: for every named (i.e. labeled) net in the top level 
  circuit a pin will be created (<class_doc href="Netlist#make_top_level_pins"/>):
  </p>

  <pre>netlist.make_top_level_pins</pre>

  <h2>Device combination</h2>

  <p>
  Combining devices is important for devices which are not 
  represented as coherent entities in the layout. Examples are:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li><b>Fingered MOS transistors:</b> MOS transistors with a large width
    are often split into multiple pieces to reduce the parasitic gate and
    diffusion resistances and capacitances. In the layout this is equivalent
    to multiple parallel transistors.
    </li>
    <li><b>Serial resistors:</b> Large resistors are often separated into 
    stripes which are then connected in a meander structure. From the device
    perspective such resistors consist of several resistors connected in 
    series.
    </li>
    <li><b>Array capacitors:</b> Large capacitors are often split into 
    smaller ones which are arranged in an array and connected in parallel.
    This helps controlling the parasitic series resistances and inductances
    and avoids manufacturing issues.
    </li>
  </ul>

  <p>
  In all these cases, the schematic usually summarizes these devices 
  into a single one with lumped parameter values (total resistance, capacitance,
  transistor width). This creates a discrepancy which "device combination"
  avoids. "Device combination" is a step in which devices are identified which
  can be combined into single devices (such as serial or parallel resistors and
  capacitors). To run device combination, use <class_doc href="Netlist#combine_devices"/>:
  </p>

  <pre>netlist.combine_devices</pre>

  <p>
  The combination of serial devices might leave floating nets (the net connecting the
  devices originally. These nets can be removed with <class_doc href="Netlist#purge_nets"/>.
  See also <class_doc href="Netlist#simplify"/>, which is wrapper for several 
  methods related to netlist normalization.
  </p>

  <p>
  It's recommended to run "make_toplevel_pins" and "purge" before this step (see below).
  </p>

  <h2>Circuit flattening (elimination)</h2>

  <p>
  It's often required to flatten circuits that do not represent a specific level of organisation but
  act as a wrapper to something else. In layouts, devices are often implemented as PCells and 
  appear as specific cells for no other reason than being implemented in a subcell. The same 
  might happen for schematic subcircuits which wrap a device. "Flattening" means that a circuit
  is removed and its contents are integrated into the calling circuits.
  </p>

  <p>
  To flatten a circuit from the extracted netlist use <class_doc href="Netlist#flatten_circuit"/>:
  </p>

  <pre>netlist.flatten_circuit("CIRCUIT_NAME")</pre>

  <p>
  The argument to "flatten_circuit" is a glob pattern (shell-like).
  For example, "NMOS*" will flatten all circuits starting with "NMOS".
  </p>

  <h2>Automatic circuit flattening (netlist alignment)</h2>

  <p>
  Instead of flattening circuits explicitly, automatic flattening is provided through
  the <a href="/about/lvs_ref_global.xml#align">align</a> method.
  </p>

  <p>
  The "align" step is optional, hence useful: it will identify cells in the 
  layout without a corresponding schematic circuit and flatten them. "Flatten"
  means their content is replicated inside their parent circuits and finally
  the cell's corresponding circuit is removed. This is useful when the layout
  contains structural cells: such cells are inserted not because the schematic
  requires them as circuit building blocks, but because layout is easier to
  create with these cells. Such cells can be PCells for devices or replication cells
  which avoid duplicate layout work. 
  </p>

  <p>
  The "align" method will also flatten schematic circuits for which there is no 
  layout cell:
  </p>

  <pre>align</pre>

  <h2>Black boxing (circuit abstraction)</h2>

  <p>
  Circuit abstraction is a technique to reduce the verification overhead. 
  At an early stage it might be useful to replace a cell by a simplified version or 
  by a raw pin frame. The circuits extracted from such cells is basically empty or 
  are intentionally simplified. But as long as there is something inside the
  cell which the parent circuit connects to, pins will be generated. These 
  pins then can be thought of as the circuit's abstraction.
  </p>

  <p>
  A useful method in this context is the "blank_circuit" method. It clears
  a circuit's innards from a netlist.  After this,
  the compare algorithm will identify both circuits as identical, provided
  they feature the same number of pins. Named pins are required to match exactly
  unless declared equivalent. Unnamed pins are treated as equivalent. To name
  pins use labels on the pin's nets inside the circuit's layout.
  </p>

  <p>
  To wipe out the innards of a circuit, use the <class_doc href="Netlist#blank_circuit"/> method:
  </p>

  <pre>netlist.blank_circuit("CIRCUIT_NAME")
schematic.blank_circuit("CIRCUIT_NAME")</pre>

  <p><b>NOTE:</b> In this version, use "blank_circuit" before "purge" or "simplify" (see below). "blank_circuit"
  sets a flag (<class_doc href="Circuit#dont_purge"/>) which prevents purging of abstract circuits.</p>

  <p>
  There is a short form for this too (<a href="/about/lvs_ref_netter.xml#blank_circuit">blank_circuit</a>). 
  In contrast to netlist-based "blank_circuit", this method can be used anywhere in the LVS script:
  </p>

  <pre>blank_circuit("CIRCUIT_NAME")</pre>

  <p>
  The argument to "blank_circuit" in both cases is a glob pattern (shell-like).
  For example, "MEMORY*" will blank out all circuits starting with the word "MEMORY".
  </p>

  <h2>Joining of symmetric nodes</h2>

  <p>
  Sometimes it is possible to omit connections in the layout because these 
  will not carry any current. This might simplify the layout and allow denser
  packing, but finally there is a mismatch between schematic and layout.
  In general, connections can be omitted if they would connect symmetric
  nodes. When symmetric nodes are swapped, the circuit will not change.
  Hence they will always carry the same potential (at least in theory) 
  and a connection between them will not carry any current. So it can 
  be omitted.
  </p>

  <p>
  The following picture describes such a situation known as "split gate configuration".
  In this case, the N1 and N2 are identical: swapping them will not change the circuit's
  topology. Hence, they will carry the same potential and the red connection is not required physically. 
  But without such a connection, the parallel transistors (top pair and bottom pair) will not be recognized
  as parallel and the pairs will not be joined into one each:
  </p>

  <p>
  <img src="lvs_symm_nodes.png"/>
  </p>

  <p>
  KLayout provides a feature (<a href="/about/lvs_ref_netter.xml#join_symmetric_nets">join_symmetric_nets</a>) 
  which will add such connections after extraction of the netlist:
  </p>

  <pre>join_symmetric_nets("NAND2")</pre>

  <p>
  This function will analyze the circuit "NAND2" in the extracted netlist and connect all symmetric 
  nodes within it. If this function is called before "combine_devices" (e.g. through
  "netlist.simplify"), this connection is already present then and parallel devices
  will be recognized and combined.
  </p>

  <p>
  The argument to "join_symmetric_nets" is a glob-style pattern. "*" will analyze and
  modify all circuits, but at the price of potentially introducing unwanted connections.
  Hence the recommendation is to use this feature on circuits which are known to 
  need it.
  </p>

  <p> 
  "join_symmetric_nets" can be used anywhere in the LVS script.
  </p>

  <h2>Purging (elimination of redundancy)</h2>

  <p>
  Extracted netlists often contain elements without a functional 
  aspect: via cells for example generate subcircuits with a single pin and
  no device. Isolated metal islands (letters, logos, fill/planarisation 
  patches) will create floating nets etc. Two methods are available to 
  purge those elements.
  </p>

  <p>
  <class_doc href="Netlist#purge"/> will remove all floating nets,
  all circuits without devices or subcircuits. <class_doc href="Netlist#purge_nets"/>
  will only purge floating nets.
  Floating nets are nets which don't connect to any device or subcircuit.
  </p>

  <pre>netlist.purge
netlist.purge_nets</pre>

  <h2>Normalization wrapper (simplification)</h2>

  <p>
  <class_doc href="Netlist#simplify"/> is a wrapper for "make_top_level_pins",
  "purge", "combine_devices" and "purge_nets" in this recommended order:
  </p>

  <pre>netlist.simplify</pre>

  <p>
  As a technical detail, "make_top_level_pins" is included in this sequence as with
  pins, nets are not considered floating. So "purge_nets" will maintain pins for
  labeled nets even if these nets are not connected to devices. This allows adding 
  optional pins while maintaining the top level circuit's interface.
  </p>

</doc>
