<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE language SYSTEM "klayout_doc.dtd">

<doc>

  <title>The Database API</title>

  <h2-index/>

  <p>
  The basic object of the database is the <class_doc href="Layout"/> object. A Layout object
  represents a layout file or a layout generated. Basically, a layout is a collection of cells and 
  geometrical shapes. The shapes are organised in layers and the cells can be instantiated in other
  cells creating a hierarchy of cells. Hence, the basic objects of the database are Layout, Cell, Shapes
  and the geometrical primitives like Box, Path, Polygon, Text and Edge.
  </p>

  <h2>The Layout class</h2>

  <keyword name="Layout"/>
  <p>
  The <class_doc href="Layout"/> object is the basic container for a layout. Multiple layouts can live within KLayout. Some are 
  stored inside the application and are created when a layout is loaded for example. However, layout objects
  can also be created as standalone objects for manipulation by Ruby scripts. Such a layout can be an isolated entity
  without connection to a view.
  </p>

  <h3>A basic sample</h3>

  <p>This is a sample how to create a layout in a layout view with one cell ("TOP"), one layer (layer 10, datatype 0) and one shape (a 1x2 micron box).
  This sample also shows how to set up the layout view properly:</p>

  <pre># create a new view (mode 1) with an empty layout
main_window = RBA::Application::instance.main_window
layout = main_window.create_layout(1).layout
layout_view = main_window.current_view

# set the database unit (shown as an example, the default is 0.001)
layout.dbu = 0.001

# create a cell
cell = layout.create_cell("TOP")

# create a layer
layer_index = layout.insert_layer(RBA::LayerInfo::new(10, 0))

# add a shape
cell.shapes(layer_index).insert(RBA::Box::new(0, 0, 1000, 2000))

# select the top cell in the view, set up the view's layer list and
# fit the viewport to the extensions of our layout
layout_view.select_cell(cell.cell_index, 0)
layout_view.add_missing_layers
layout_view.zoom_fit
</pre>

  <p>It is also possible to create a standalone layout. Here is an example how to create the layout
  without a connection to a view and save that layout to a file:
  </p>

  <pre># create the layout
layout = RBA::Layout::new

# set the database unit (shown as an example, the default is 0.001)
layout.dbu = 0.001

# create a cell
cell = layout.create_cell("TOP")

# create a layer
layer_index = layout.insert_layer(RBA::LayerInfo::new(10, 0))

# add a shape
cell.shapes(layer_index).insert(RBA::Box::new(0, 0, 1000, 2000))

# save the layout
layout.write("my_layout.gds")</pre>

  <h3>Overview over the Layout object</h3>
  <keyword name="Layout Overview"/>

  <p>
  The basic building blocks of layouts are layers and cells. Layers are not individual objects. Instead, a layer
  is rather an index and the various methods allow addressing shapes inside layers by using that index. However,
  the layout object stores the layer properties, i.e. the layer and datatype number.
  </p>

  <p>
  Cells are represented by <class_doc href="Cell"/> objects which are described later. Cells are often
  referred to by a cell index which is basically an ID which allows identification of 
  a cell without having to keep a reference. The Layout object allows converting of a cell index to a cell reference
  with the <class_doc href="Layout#cell"/> method. Cells can be instantiated inside other cells. Instances are
  described by <class_doc href="CellInstArray"/> objects.
  </p>

  <p>
  Another important property of the layout object is the database unit. In the layout, all geometrical coordinates are
  stored as integer values for efficiency. The database unit specifies the length of one unit in micrometers. 
  The database unit can be accessed with the <class_doc href="Layout#dbu"/> attribute. Changing the database unit effectively scales
  a layout. Often the database unit is a fixed value and compatibility between different layouts in a flow 
  often demands use of a specific database unit. Hence, changing the value of the database unit is possible
  but requires some careful consideration.
  </p>

  <p>
  KLayout provides certain "working objects" - i.e. standalone geometry primitives that can be used in a number
  of low-level algorithms. For example, for rectangles, the <class_doc href="Box"/> object is provided. These objects
  represent coordinates as integer units as they are compatible with the internal objects from the database. 
  By convention, these coordinates are interpreted as multiple of database units, i.e. a width of "100" for a box 
  converts to "100 nm" for a database unit of 1 nm.
  These working objects are described in the "Geometry API" section.
  </p>

  <p>
  In parallel to these objects, there exist floating-point coordinate objects. They are identified by a "D" prefix in 
  the class name. For example, the floating-point twin of "Box" is  <class_doc href="DBox"/>. By convention, the 
  coordinates of these objects are interpreted as micrometers. Hence, these objects represent physical dimensions
  without needing a database unit.
  </p>

  <p>
  Some algorithms, as the ones provided by the "Region" class, cannot act on floating-point objects. Hence their 
  use is somewhat limited. Still is it convenient to work with such objects in coding layout generators for example.
  The Layout database allows retrieving primitives in both integer (database unit) and floating-point (micrometer forms)
  and also accepts both forms in most places. Conversion to the internal integer-coordinate representation happens
  automatically.
  </p>

  <p>
  The Layout object keeps shapes (texts, polygons, boxes, paths etc.) on "layers". A layer is a collection of
  shapes. A layout features a set of layers and each cell provides space for each layer. The shapes are stored
  inside the cells while the layers are managed by the layout.
  For doing so, the Layout object keeps layers as a table of <class_doc href="LayerInfo"/> objects. The LayerInfo object
  carries information about the description of a layer, for example layer and datatype number and/or the layer name.
  A layer is basically 
  just an index in that table. Layers can be created using the <class_doc href="Layout#insert_layer"/> method. Each layer is present
  in every cell and inside a cell, a shape storage for each layer is provided.
  </p>

  <p>
  Inside the layout object, shapes are kept with integer coordinates. The physical units can be obtained
  by multiplying the integer coordinates with the database unit. The integer type objects are <class_doc href="Box"/>, <class_doc href="Polygon"/>
  etc. Most objects also support floating-point coordinate objects (<class_doc href="DBox"/>, <class_doc href="DPolygon"/> etc.). 
  These objects are then given in micrometer units - i.e. already multiplied by the database unit. 
  If using these objects, keep in mind that internally they are still integer-type objects. This means, 
  rounding to the database will happen and if you change the database unit, the objects will effectively scale.
  </p>

  <p>
  A Layout object provides some basic layout manipulation and query methods. For example, it provides a method
  to retrieve shapes touching or overlapping a certain rectangular region of a cell. It also provides a clip method which
  extracts a rectangular region from a layout 
  (<class_doc href="Layout#clip"/>, <class_doc href="Layout#clip_into"/>, <class_doc href="Layout#multi_clip"/>, <class_doc href="Layout#multi_clip_into"/>). It provides methods to delete cells and cell trees and (<class_doc href="Layout#delete_cell"/>, <class_doc href="Layout#delete_cell_rec"/>, <class_doc href="Layout#delete_cells"/>, 
  <class_doc href="Layout#prune_cell"/>, <class_doc href="Layout#prune_subcells"/>). There are also methods to manipulate layers (<class_doc href="Layout#clear_layer"/>, <class_doc href="Layout#copy_layer"/>, <class_doc href="Layout#move_layer"/>, <class_doc href="Layout#delete_layer"/>).
  </p>

  <p>
  Some convenience functions are provide to read and write a layout from or to a file. The <class_doc href="Layout#read"/> method reads a
  layout from a file. It basically merges the contents of the file with the layout so it's possible to 
  combine multiple files by using read more than once. The method comes in two flavors: a simple one and one
  that allows specification of reader options with a <class_doc href="LoadLayoutOptions"/> object.
  There is also a <class_doc href="Layout#write"/> method which writes the layout to a file. The simple form writes the layout to
  a file and the file type is determined by the file extension. A full-featured version exists which allows 
  to specify the format and many more options with a <class_doc href="SaveLayoutOptions"/> object.
  </p>

  <p>
  Layouts can also import cells from Libraries (<class_doc href="Library"/>). Such imported cells are basically
  cells linked to another cell inside the library. Library cells are imported using the <class_doc href="Layout#add_lib_cell"/> method.
  This method creates a "proxy" cell which is a copy of the library cell but is linked to the library. As long as
  the library is present in the system, this link is maintained and stored in the layout files. If the link is lost
  because the library is removed, the proxy cell becomes a normal cell.
  Such proxy cells basically behave like normal cells but should not be manipulated.
  </p>

  <p>
  Layout objects are also responsible for handling properties. Properties are basically arbitrary sets
  of data (key/value pairs) attached to shapes, cells or instances. For efficiency, the property data is not
  attached to every shape, cell or instance. Instead, the layout object manages different property sets and
  associate each distinct set with an integer ID. The shape, cell or cell instance only stores that ID. 
  To create, query or change property sets, the layout object provides the <class_doc href="Layout#properties"/> and
  <class_doc href="Layout#properties_id"/> methods. Since that is inconvenient, shapes, cells and instances provide 
  access to the properties by providing methods to set, get and delete properties from the set (for example <class_doc href="Shape#property"/>, 
  <class_doc href="Shape#delete_property"/> and <class_doc href="Shape#set_property"/>). Internally, these methods
  create a new ID if necessary and assign that ID to the shape, cell or instance.
  </p>

  <p>
  A layout can provide and import PCells. PCells are cells that provide its geometry through program code
  (for example written in Ruby) and provide parameters which can be adjusted to change the appearance of the 
  cell. For each PCell a "declaration" must be provided which basically contains the code for the 
  PCell and some information about the parameters provided by the PCell. PCells are stored in the layout
  and are referred to by a PCell ID (an integer). PCells are added to a layout using <class_doc href="Layout#register_pcell"/> and 
  retrieved by ID or name using <class_doc href="Layout#pcell_declaration"/>. PCells are instantiated with a specific parameter set
  using the <class_doc href="Layout#add_pcell_variant"/>. This method creates a cell representing the layout generated by the 
  PCell code for a particular set of parameters. The layout internally caches the PCell layouts so the PCell 
  code is executed only if a new parameter set is requested. Usually PCells are provided through libraries.
  In that case, the library provides the PCell variant through <class_doc href="Layout#add_pcell_variant"/> which is imported into the 
  target layout through <class_doc href="Layout#add_lib_cell"/>. There is a overload of <class_doc href="Layout#add_pcell_variant"/> which combines both
  steps.
  </p>

  <p>
  The following code demonstrates how to create a PCell (in that case a "TEXT" cell from the "Basic" library):
  </p>

  <pre>ly = RBA::Layout.new
top = ly.add_cell("TOP")

# Find the lib
lib = RBA::Library.library_by_name("Basic")
lib || raise("Unknown lib 'Basic'")

# Find the pcell
pcell_decl = lib.layout.pcell_declaration("TEXT")
pcell_decl || raise("Unknown PCell 'TEXT'")

# Set the parameters (text string, layer to 10/0, magnification to 2.5)
param = { "text" =&gt; "KLAYOUT RULES", "layer" =&gt; RBA::LayerInfo::new(10, 0), "mag" =&gt; 2.5 }

# Build a param array using the param hash as a source.
# Fill all remaining parameter with default values.
pv = pcell_decl.get_parameters.collect do |p|
  param[p.name] || p.default
end

# Create a PCell variant cell
pcell_var = ly.add_pcell_variant(lib, pcell_decl.id, pv)

# Instantiate that cell
t = RBA::Trans::new(RBA::Trans::r90, 0, 0)
pcell_inst = ly.cell(top).insert(RBA::CellInstArray::new(pcell_var, t))</pre>

  <h3>Editable mode</h3>
  <keyword name="Editable Mode"/>

  <p>
  A layout can exist in two flavors: editable and non-editable. In editable mode, some optimisations
  are disabled. For example, OASIS shape arrays are expanded into single shapes. This enables manipulation
  of the database. For example, the shape replacement, property manipulation and other operations are
  only possible in editable mode. On the other hand, the memory footprint of a layout may be larger
  in editable mode. Independent of the mode, layouts can be created and cells, instances and shapes
  can be added, but not manipulated.
  </p>

  <p>
  A layout object living in the application is created in editable or non-editable mode depending on
  the application setting. Layout objects explicitly created by RBA code can either be in editable
  or non-editable mode:
  </p>

  <pre>editable_layout = RBA::Layout.new
non_editable_layout = RBA::Layout.new(false)</pre>
  
  <p>
  The <class_doc href="Layout#is_editable?"/> method returns true, if a layout is in editable mode. Once the layout is
  created, the editable mode cannot be changed.
  </p>

  <h3>Meta information</h3>
  <keyword name="Meta"/>
  <keyword name="Meta Information"/>

  <p>A layout object and cell objects can keep arbitrary meta data in the form of key/value pairs. This meta data is 
  extracted during the reading of a layout and will reflect special properties of the layout file.
  For example, the GDS2 library name is available as meta information with key "libname".
  </p>

  <p>The layout object offers methods to retrieve that information: <class_doc href="Layout#each_meta_info"/> will 
  iterate over the meta data (returning a <class_doc href="LayoutMetaInfo"/> object). <class_doc href="Layout#meta_info_value"/>
  will get the value for a given name. <class_doc href="Layout#add_meta_info"/> will add a new meta information object
  and <class_doc href="Layout#remove_meta_info"/> will delete one. 
  Equivalent methods exist for the "Cell" class.
  </p>

  <p>
  Meta information is a different concept than properties. While properties are native to the stream format 
  used, meta information is a KLayout extension. It is mapped to properties in OASIS in the same way, PCell
  context information is stored. For GDS2, KLayout provides a special context container inside the GDS2 file 
  to store that information.
  </p>

  <p>
  Meta information is not subject to the stream format's limitations. For example, keys can be of any type
  and values can be arrays, dicts or even higher-level, string-serializable objects such as "Box". 
  There is also no restriction on size of the attached data, in contrast to properties, where GDS2 imposes 
  some limitations on the string length for example.
  </p>

  <h3>Cell related methods</h3>
  <keyword name="Cell"/>

  <p>Cells can be created using the <class_doc href="Layout#create_cell"/> method. This method expects a cell name. If a cell with that
  name already exists, a new name is generated by appending a suffix. The method returns the Cell object of the new
  cell. <class_doc href="Layout#rename_cell"/> or <class_doc href="Cell#name="/> can be used to change the name of a cell.
  The Cell object for a given name can be obtained with <class_doc href="Layout#cell"/> which returns the Cell
  object or nil if no cell with that name exists.
  </p>

  <p>The cell name can be obtained from the cell index with the <class_doc href="Layout#cell_name"/> method or <class_doc href="Cell#name"/>).
  <class_doc href="Layout#has_cell?"/> can be used to determine whether a cell with
  the given name exists. <class_doc href="Layout#is_valid_cell_index?"/> can be used to determine whether a given index is a valid cell
  index. <class_doc href="Layout#cells"/> returns the number of cells in the layout.
  To work with cells, the Cell object is required. It can be obtained from the cell index using the <class_doc href="Layout#cell"/> method.
  </p>

  <p>
  The top cell of a layout can be obtained using <class_doc href="Layout#top_cell"/>. If multiple top cells exist,
  this method will raise an exception. In that case, <class_doc href="Layout#top_cells"/> can be used to obtain 
  all top cells.
  </p>

  <p>All cells in the layout can be iterated using the <class_doc href="Layout#each_cell"/> iterator. All top cells (cells which are 
  not instantiated itself) can be iterated with the <class_doc href="Layout#each_top_cell"/> iterator. The cells can be iterated bottom-up
  (all child cells come before their parents) or top-down (all parents come before their children) using the 
  <class_doc href="Layout#each_cell_bottom_up"/> or <class_doc href="Layout#each_cell_top_down"/>.
  </p>

  <p>
  <class_doc href="Layout#delete_cell"/> deletes a cell. This method will keep the child cells, which may become top cells because their parent
  cell is deleted. <class_doc href="Layout#delete_cells"/> deletes multiple cells and is more efficient than deleting cell by cell. 
  <class_doc href="Layout#delete_cell_rec"/> will delete a cell and all child cells (direct and indirect), irregardless whether they
  are used otherwise or not. <class_doc href="Layout#prune_cell"/> does the same but is somewhat more sensitive in that respect and
  does not delete child cells if they are instantiated by parents not in the cell tree below the cell being deleted.
  <class_doc href="Layout#prune_subcells"/> as prune_cell deletes the child cells or a cell but in contrast to prune_cell does not delete the 
  cell itself.
  </p>

  <h3>Layer related methods</h3>
  <keyword name="Layer"/>

  <p><class_doc href="Layout#insert_layer"/> creates a new layer in the layout. The layer will be available to all cells. This method 
  receives a <class_doc href="LayerInfo"/> object which holds the information about the layer's name, layer
  and datatype. It returns a layer index which can be used to address shapes in the cells. <class_doc href="Layout#insert_layer_at"/> 
  can be used to create a layer with a specific layer index, provided that index is not used yet.</p>

  <p><class_doc href="Layout#is_valid_layer?"/> can be used to determine whether a layer index is a valid index. <class_doc href="Layout#layer_indices"/> 
  returns a list of indexes of all layers present. <class_doc href="Layout#layers"/> returns the number of layers present.</p>

  <p><class_doc href="Layout#find_layer"/>Returns the layer index for a given layer in various flavors.
  <class_doc href="Layout#layer"/> finds or creates a layer if it does not exist yet. Again, the layer
  can be given in various flavors - for example by layer and datatype, by name or with a <class_doc href="LayerInfo"/> object.</p>

  <p><class_doc href="Layout#set_info"/> can be used to change the LayerInfo object for a layer. <class_doc href="Layout#get_info"/> returns the LayerInfo
  object for a layer. To modify the information, obtain the information with get_info, modify it, and set the 
  new information with set_info:</p>

  <pre>lv = RBA::Application::instance.main_window.current_view
ly = lv.current_cellview.layout
info = ly.get_info(0)
info.layer = 100
ly.set_info(0, info)
lv.add_missing_layers
lv.remove_unused_layers</pre>

  <p>The previous sample changes the layer number for layer index 0 to 100. "add_missing_layers" and "remove_unused_layers" will create 
  new layer entries in the layer list and remove the entry for the previous layer.</p>

  <p>For special purposes, special (temporary) layers can be created in the layout. Those layers basically behave like 
  normal layers but don't appear in the layer list and are not saved to a file. Special layers can be created using
  <class_doc href="Layout#insert_special_layer"/> and <class_doc href="Layout#insert_special_layer_at"/>. <class_doc href="Layout#is_special_layer?"/> returns true if a given index
  is a special layer.
  </p>

  <p>In addition, a layout contains a special layer which is used to implement the "guiding shape" feature of PCells.
  It is a special layer that serves as a container for shapes which parametrize PCells. The index of that layer can be
  obtained with <class_doc href="Layout#guiding_shape_layer"/>.</p>

  <p>A list of the indexes for all layers inside the layout can be obtained with <class_doc href="Layout#layer_indexes"/>. 
  A corresponding list of LayerInfo objects can be obtained with <class_doc href="Layout#layer_infos"/>.
  </p>

  <h3>Recursive full or region queries</h3>
  <keyword name="Region Query"/>
  <keyword name="Recursive Region Query"/>

  <p>
  A layout provides methods to retrieve shapes recursively. That means, that the shapes are delivered from all 
  cells instantiated below a given top cell. Cells instantiated multiple times are also visited multiple times.
  While the shapes are delivered, information is provided what cell instances the
  specific shape instance is found in.
  </p>

  <p>
  Recursive shape retrieval is done through a iterator, the <class_doc href="RecursiveShapeIterator"/>.
  This object delivers one shape each time. A RecursiveShapeIterator is created for example using the <class_doc href="Layout#begin_shapes"/> method.
  This method requires the cell index of the starting (initial) cell and a layer index.
  This code demonstrates how to use the RecursiveShapeIterator:
  </p>

  <pre>layout = RBA::Application::instance.main_window.current_view.active_cellview.layout
# start iterating shapes from cell "TOP", layer index 0
si = layout.begin_shapes(layout.cell_by_name("TOP"), 0)
while !si.at_end?
  puts si.shape.to_s + " with transformation " + si.trans.to_s
  si.next
end</pre>

  <p>
  The RecursiveShapeIterator's shape method delivers a shape reference (see description of the Shape class or <class_doc href="Shape"/>)
  which basically points to a shape inside a cell. Since the cell may be a child cell of the initial cell 
  the RecursiveShapeIterator was created with, in general a transformation is present that tells how the cell's
  content shows up in the initial cell. The generic form of that transformation is a <class_doc href="CplxTrans"/> object
  which is delivered by the RecursiveShapeIterator's "trans" method. This transformation renders floating-point coordinates which
  is precise but not a suitable representation for transforming shapes into a form compatible with the database. 
  For that purpose, a <class_doc href="ICplxTrans"/> object is provided as well through the "itrans" method.
  This transformation renders integer coordinates which may imply rounding effects in some cases. The RecursiveShapeIterator
  delivers the cell from which the current shape is taken through the "cell_index" method.
  </p>

  <p>
  A RecursiveShapeIterator can be configured to retrieve only certain type of shapes (i.e. boxes, texts etc.).
  To do so, set the shape_flags attribute of the shape iterator before using it:
  </p>

  <pre>layout = RBA::Application::instance.main_window.current_view.active_cellview.layout
# start iterating shapes from cell "TOP", layer index 0
si = layout.begin_shapes(layout.cell_by_name("TOP"), 0)
si.shape_flags = RBA::Shapes::SBoxes
while !si.at_end?
  puts si.shape.to_s + " with transformation " + si.trans.to_s
  si.next
end</pre>

  <p>
  Also the maximum depth at which the RecursiveShapeIterator will traverse the hierarchy can be set using the "max_depth"
  attribute. Setting this attribute to 0 will report only shapes from the initial cell. The depth must be set before the 
  first shape is retrieved.
  </p>

  <p>
  The RecursiveShapeIterator can also deliver shapes from a region. The region is a rectangle specified in coordinates
  of the initial cell. To create a RecursiveShapeIterator that only delivers shapes inside that region use the 
  <class_doc href="Layout#begin_shapes_touching"/> or <class_doc href="Layout#begin_shapes_overlapping"/> methods of the Layout object.
  These methods expect a Box object that specifies that rectangle. All shapes delivered will either touch or overlap
  that box when projected into the initial cell.
  </p>

  <p>
  Shape manipulations should be avoided inside loops that iterate over shapes using a RecursiveShapeIterator.
  The reason is that shape manipulations may invalidate the internal state of the RecursiveShapeIterator.
  Instead, collect all shape references that need to be manipulated in an array and do the manipulations later.
  </p>

  <h3>Properties</h3>
  <keyword name="Properties"/>

  <p>
  As stated earlier, shapes and other objects can carry an arbitrary number of user properties in form of key/value pairs.
  For efficiency, these properties are not stored directly, but in form of a properties ID, which identifies
  a unique set of properties.
  </p>

  <p>
  The objects that can carry properties are shapes (<class_doc href="Shape"/>), instances (<class_doc href="Instance"/>),
  Cells (<class_doc href="Cell"/>) and the Layout object itself (<class_doc href="Layout"/>). All these objects
  have a "prop_id" method that allows retrieving the properties ID. There is also a setter to change the properties ID.
  </p>

  <p>
  As it is not quite convenient to work with properties IDs, there are methods to get or manipulate the properties directly.
  Those are:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li> "property" (<class_doc href="Shape#property"/>, <class_doc href="Instance#property"/>, 
      <class_doc href="Cell#property"/> and <class_doc href="Layout#property"/>) to get the property value 
      for a specific key.
    </li>
    <li> "set_property" (<class_doc href="Shape#set_property"/>, <class_doc href="Instance#set_property"/>, 
      <class_doc href="Cell#set_property"/> and <class_doc href="Layout#set_property"/>) to change or set the property value 
      for a specific key.
    </li>
    <li> "delete_property" (<class_doc href="Shape#delete_property"/>, <class_doc href="Instance#delete_property"/>, 
      <class_doc href="Cell#delete_property"/> and <class_doc href="Layout#delete_property"/>) to remove a specific key
      from the properties.
    </li>
    <li> "properties" (<class_doc href="Shape#properties"/>, <class_doc href="Instance#properties"/>, 
      and <class_doc href="Cell#properties"/>) to get the properties as a hash (dict).
      For the "Layout" object this method is called "properties_hash" (<class_doc href="Layout#properties_hash"/>).
      For historical reasons, this class also has a method "properties_array" (<class_doc href="Layout#properties_array"/>)
      that delivers the properties as an array of key/value pairs.
    </li>
    <li> "has_prop_id?" (<class_doc href="Shape#has_prop_id?"/>, <class_doc href="Instance#has_prop_id?"/>, 
      <class_doc href="Cell#has_prop_id?"/> and <class_doc href="Layout#has_prop_id?"/>) is a predicate indicating
      that properties are attached to the object.
    </li>
  </ul>

  <p>
  Properties IDs identify a property set uniquely, so identity of the IDs implies identity of the properties set.
  In the same fashion, different IDs mean different properties sets.
  The ID is an arbitrary integer value and will change between invocations of the program.
  The ID value 0 is reserved for "no properties" or an empty property set.
  </p>

  <p>
  Sometimes it is required to work with properties IDs directly.
  The Layout object provides four class methods to convert properties IDs to hashes (dicts) or lists 
  back and forth:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li> "properties_id" gets the properties ID from an array or hash of properties (<class_doc href="Layout#properties_id"/>).
      If used with an array, the array elements need to be key/value pairs.</li>
    <li> "properties_array" gets the properties as an array of key/value pairs from a properties ID (<class_doc href="Layout#properties_array"/>).</li>
    <li> "properties_dict" gets the properties as a hash (dict) from a properties ID (<class_doc href="Layout#properties_dict"/>).</li>
    <li> "property" gets a property value for a given key from a properties ID (<class_doc href="Layout#property"/>).</li>
  </ul>

  <p>
  Here is a sample for working with properties IDs:
  </p>

  <pre>layout = RBA::Layout::new

# Populate the layout with a layer, a cell and one shape

l1 = layout.layer(1, 0)
top = layout.create_cell("TOP")
box = top.shapes(l1).insert(RBA::Box::new(0, 0, 100, 200))

# Use properties IDs to set initial properties

props = { 1 => "value for key #1", 2 => "value for key #2" }
prop_id = RBA::Layout::properties_id(props)

# same as:
# box.set_property(1, "value for key #1")
# box.set_property(2, "value for key #2")
box.prop_id = prop_id

# Change key 1 property
# same as:
# box.set_property(1, "one")

props = RBA::Layout::properties_hash(box.prop_id)
props[1] = "one"
box.prop_id = RBA::Layout::properties_id(props)</pre>

  <p>
  Please note that replacing a property ID and modifying the properties usually invalidates any iterators and should 
  not be done in a loop over shapes.
  </p>

  <p>
  <b>Note:</b> Although property keys can basically be any type, the GDS2 format does not have string names for properties. 
  Property keys should be positive integers for GDS2.
  OASIS, on the other hand, can handle string and numeric property "names". When saving layouts in GDS2 format, KLayout tries
  to convert the properties' names into numbers if possible (i.e. if it sees that the string is a number). If it can't, then
  the property is not saved. When the layout is read by KLayout upon opening, the property keys will be read as integers.
  </p>

  <p>
  Values can be strings or numerical for OASIS. In GDS2, values are converted to strings always.
  </p>

  <h2>The LayerInfo class</h2>

  <keyword name="LayerInfo"/>
  <p>
  The <class_doc href="LayerInfo"/> object encapsulates the layer's naming properties. 
  In GDS2, a layer is described by a layer number and datatype number. In OASIS, a text name can be added
  to that description. In other formats like DXF, a layer has just a text name.
  </p>

  <p>
  The LayerInfo object thus has a twofold identity: a numeric identity (layer and datatype number) and 
  a text layer name. Both properties can be specified. In that case, the numeric identity has precedence
  over the text name.
  </p>

  <p>
  When a layout is loaded, LayerInfo objects are used to represent a layer's naming properties in 
  the Layout object. The LayerInfo object associated with a layer can be retrieved using the Layout's
  "get_info" method. It can be set using the "set_info" method. In general, the LayerInfo property is
  detached from the layer index, so it can be assigned and manipulated freely. 
  </p>

  <p>
  The default constructor of LayerInfo will create a nameless object. Nameless layers are not saved
  to any file and can be used for internal purposes such as temporary or intermediate layers. 
  </p>

  <p>
  The <class_doc href="LayerInfo#layer"/> attribute allows read and write access to the layer number. <class_doc href="LayerInfo#datatype"/> is the
  attribute for the datatype number. <class_doc href="LayerInfo#name"/> gives access to the text name. <class_doc href="LayerInfo#is_named?"/> returns
  true, if the LayerInfo object represents a named layer (no layer or datatype number are specified). 
  <class_doc href="LayerInfo#is_equivalent?"/> compares two LayerInfo objects and returns true, if both denote the same
  layer. This is not exact equivalence but follows the logical precedence: two layers are equivalent
  if layer or datatype number match (in that case the text name is ignored) or, if no layer and datatype
  number are specified, the name matches exactly.
  </p>

  <p>
  LayerInfo objects supply a hash value (<class_doc href="LayerInfo#hash"/>) and can therefore be used as
  keys in Ruby hashes.
  </p>

  <h2>The Cell class</h2>

  <keyword name="Cell"/>
  <p>
  After the Layout object, the <class_doc href="Cell"/> object is the most fundamental object in KLayout's database 
  API. It represents a cell, which itself is a collection of shapes per layer
  and instances of other cells. The methods provided by the Cell class deal with either the shape or
  the instance aspect. A cell is also responsible for handling parts of the PCell scheme, either for
  the cell itself (if it is an incarnation of a PCell) or instances of PCells.
  </p>

  <p>
  A cell has a name which can be retrieved using the <class_doc href="Cell#name"/> method and which can be set
  using the <class_doc href="Cell#name="/> method. Setting the name is equivalent to using the Layout's "rename_cell" method.
  <class_doc href="Cell#basic_name"/> delivers the PCell or library cell name for cells imported from a library or PCell variants. "name"
  will deliver an internal unique name in that case. <class_doc href="Cell#display_title"/> is a string that encodes library name
  and PCell parameters as well and can be used as a descriptive title for the cell in user interfaces.
  </p>

  <p>
  If the cell is a library cell (a "proxy"), it will have a database name (something like "TEXT$1") and a qualified
  name which states the library and the cell name separated with a dot (i.e. "Basic.TEXT"). The qualified name
  is not neccessarily unique. The qualified name of the cell can be obtained with <class_doc href="Cell#qname"/>.
  </p>

  <p>
  A cell that represents a cell imported from a library or a PCell variant (or both) is called a proxy cell.
  For such cells, <class_doc href="Cell#is_proxy?"/> returns true. Such cells should not be manipulated since they may be refreshed
  when required and the original state is restored. <class_doc href="Cell#is_library_cell?"/> and <class_doc href="Cell#is_pcell_variant?"/> deliver
  a more detailed information about the nature of the proxy cell.
  </p>

  <p>
  The layout that the cell lives in can be retrieved with the <class_doc href="Cell#layout"/> method. If the cell is 
  created standalone (without layout), this method returns nil. In that case, a cell is not named either.
  </p>

  <p>
  A cell can be a "ghost cell". A ghost cell is an empty cell which is not written to a layout write and 
  created when a layout file is read with an unsatisfied reference. Unsatisfied references are present 
  in some GDS2 files which represent partial layouts. By simple merging of two GDS2 files, such references can be
  made true instances, when another file contributes the cell for that reference. KLayout supports such 
  unsatisfied references by providing the "ghost cells" which serve as a instance target but are not written.
  Ghost cells are simply cells where the <class_doc href="Cell#is_ghost_cell?"/> attribute is true. An empty cell can be made
  a ghost cell by setting the <class_doc href="Cell#ghost_cell="/> property.
  </p>

  <p>
  A cell has a bounding box which includes child cells as well. KLayout keeps a per-layer bounding box, so it's 
  very simple to tell whether a cell is empty in a certain layer (including the hierarchy below). In that case 
  the per-layer bounding box is an empty box. The overall bounding box can be derived with the <class_doc href="Cell#bbox"/> method.
  The per-layer bounding box can be derived with the <class_doc href="Cell#bbox_per_layer"/> method.
  </p>

  <p>
  Cells can be marked as "ghost cells" using the <class_doc href="Cell#ghost_cell="/>. Ghost cells
  are not saved into GDS2 files (but their references are). Also, ghost cells act as "placeholders" for cells - 
  for example if a cell is pasted into a layout, it will replace any ghost cell with the same name.
  If a normal cell with the same name exists, a copy will be created instead. A cell can be asked whether
  it is a ghost cell using <class_doc href="Cell#is_ghost_cell?"/>.
  </p>

  <p>
  Starting with version 0.23, cells can have properties as well, but writing cell properties to layout
  files is subject to some restrictions. Properties are only written to GDS2 if a special option is enabled
  because a potentially incompatible extension of GDS2 is used to store the properties. OASIS files 
  support cell properties without restrictions.
  </p>

  <h3>Cells and shapes</h3>

  <p>
  A cell carries a set of geometrical shapes, organised in layers. A layer is specified by a layer index. The layer index
  is managed by the Layout object. It is basically an integer that identifies the layer in the layout. 
  The shapes are stored in containers of the <class_doc href="Shapes"/> class. Given a layer index, the 
  shapes object can be obtained from the cell through the <class_doc href="Cell#shapes"/> method:
  </p>

  <pre>shapes = cell.shapes(layer_index)
shapes.each do |shape|
  puts shape.to_s
end</pre>

  <p>
  The same can be achieved by directly iterating over the shapes in the cell:
  </p>

  <pre>cell.each_shape(layer_index) do |shape|
  puts shape.to_s
end</pre>

  <p>
  That iterator also allows specification of a filter so it delivers only a certain subset, i.e. only text objects.
  See <class_doc href="Cell"/> and <class_doc href="Shapes"/> for more details.
  </p>

  <p>
  There are iterators that deliver shapes within a rectangular region, either overlapping or touching that
  region (<class_doc href="Cell#each_overlapping_shape"/>, <class_doc href="Cell#each_touching_shape"/>). They basically work like the "each_shape"
  iterator. Please note that these iterators are not recursive, i.e. they don't deliver shapes from child cells.
  Recursive iteration can be performed using Layout's "begin_shapes" method and the RecursiveShapeIterator object.
  </p>

  <p>
  All shapes in a cell can be cleared using <class_doc href="Cell#clear_shapes"/>. A single layer can be cleared using the <class_doc href="Cell#clear"/> method
  with the layer index to clear. Both methods are not recursive, i.e. they only clear the shapes on the given cell, not on 
  the child cells.
  </p>

  <p>Layers can be copied using the <class_doc href="Cell#copy"/> method. The shapes of a layer can be moved to another layer using the <class_doc href="Cell#move"/>
  method. In both cases, the target layer is not overwritten, but the shapes from the source layer are added to the target layer.
  <class_doc href="Cell#swap"/> will swap the shapes of two layers. In all these cases, the operation is local on the cell, i.e. child cells are
  not affected.
  </p>

  <p>
  Shapes within a cell are represented as <class_doc href="Shape"/> objects. A shape object is a generic object 
  which represents either a polygon, a box, a path, a text or an edge object. Shapes provide some generic methods
  such as <class_doc href="Shape#bbox"/> to retrieve the bounding box or <class_doc href="Shape#transform"/>. Shapes 
  act as "pointers" to geometrical objects inside the database. Manipulating a shape will also manipulate the 
  database object.
  </p>

  <p>
  To work with specific kind of shapes, the working classes such as <class_doc href="Polygon"/> are provided. Shapes
  can be converted into these working objects. The working objects are not related to the layout object and not
  having a connection to the layout makes them lightweight objects. A usual way of manipulating a shape is to
  translate it to a working object, modify that and assign the working object back to the shape.
  </p>

  <p>
  Interfaces to floating-point working classes such as <class_doc href="DPolygon"/> are provided too. By convention
  such objects represent shapes in micrometer units. If such an object is requested from the shapes container it
  is converted from an integer-type object in database units to a floating-point type object in micrometer units
  by multiplying with the database unit. When sending such an object to the Shapes container the same happens in 
  reverse. Internally, the integer type is used.
  </p>
  
  <h3>Cells and hierarchy</h3>

  <p>
  The direct children of a cell can be iterated with <class_doc href="Cell#each_child_cell"/>. That iterator delivers the cell index of
  each child cell of the cell. Similar, there is a <class_doc href="Cell#each_parent_cell"/> iterator. It delivers the cell indexes of
  all cells calling that cells. For a top cell that iterator delivers nothing. <class_doc href="Cell#is_leaf?"/> returns true, if the 
  cell does not have child cells. <class_doc href="Cell#is_top?"/> returns true, if the cell is top cell. 
  </p>

  <p>
  Cells and their children form a directed acyclic cell graph. That means, no cell may instantiate a cell which itself calls the
  cell whether directly or indirectly. There is a set of cells called by a given cell, either directly or indirectly through 
  children of the cell. That set is the "called" cell set. That cell set can be obtained with the <class_doc href="Cell#called_cells"/> method in 
  form of an array of cell indexes.
  </p>

  <p>
  Similar, there is a set of cells calling a cell, either directly or indirectly. That set of cells can be obtained with 
  the <class_doc href="Cell#caller_cells"/> method. For a top cell that set is empty. 
  </p>

  <p>
  The number of hierarchy levels can be obtained with <class_doc href="Cell#hierarchy_levels"/>. This method delivers the length of the longest path
  to a leaf cell. A leaf cell has a hierarchy level count of 0. 
  </p>

  <p>
  A cell can be flattened using <class_doc href="Cell#flatten"/>.
  Child cells can be removed using <class_doc href="Cell#prune_subcells"/>.
  The cell can be removed with <class_doc href="Cell#delete"/> or <class_doc href="Cell#prune_cell"/>. The
  latter will also remove any child cells which are not used otherwise.
  </p>

  <h3>Copying information between cells</h3>

  <p>
  Instances can be copied from one cell to another using <class_doc href="Cell#copy_instances"/>. 
  Shapes can be copied using <class_doc href="Cell#copy_shapes"/>. The latter method supports 
  layer conversions by employing a <class_doc href="LayerMapping"/> object to specify input and 
  output layers. In addition, shapes can be copied to another layout which automatically performs
  database unit conversion if necessary.
  </p>

  <p>
  A full cell tree can be copied using <class_doc href="Cell#copy_tree"/>. This method will 
  create a new hierarchy below the target cell matching the source cell's hierarchy and 
  copy all shapes from source to target using that new hierarchy. Source and target cell 
  may reside in different layouts and database unit conversion is done automatically.
  </p>

  <p>
  The content of a cell can be copied to another cell hierarchically using <class_doc href="Cell#copy_tree_shapes"/>, 
  provided a cell mapping exists. A cell mapping specifies, how child cells of the source cell are identified
  in the target, which can be a different layout. For the cell mapping a <class_doc href="CellMapping"/> object is
  employed. In addition, a <class_doc href="LayerMapping"/> object can be used to specify layer mapping to 
  the target. If no cell mapping is provided, shapes are flattened into the next possible parent, which provides
  a way to creating flat copies of cells.
  "copy_tree" is a convenience method and is a special case of "copy_tree_shapes".
  </p>

  <p>
  For all methods, "move" flavors are available (<class_doc href="Cell#move_instances"/>, 
  <class_doc href="Cell#move_shapes"/>, <class_doc href="Cell#move_tree"/> and <class_doc href="Cell#move_tree_shapes"/>), 
  which not only copy the information but also remove the respective objects in the source 
  cell. That somewhat reduces the memory required for such operations.
  </p>

  <h3>Cells and instances</h3>

  <p>
  A cell also plays a role as container for the instances. An instance describes a cell that is placed into another cell.
  Technically an instance is a combination of a cell reference and a transformation. Raw instances are represented by <class_doc href="CellInstArray"/>
  objects. Instances inside a cell are referred to by <class_doc href="Instance"/> objects.
  An Instance object is basically a pointer into a CellInstArray stored inside a cell and associates properties with raw
  instances for example.
  </p>

  <p>
  Instances can be created by using the various <class_doc href="Cell#insert"/> methods of Cell. Instances can have properties, so a property ID
  can be provided (see Layout class for a discussion about property ID's). Instances can be deleted using the <class_doc href="Cell#erase"/> method.
  All instances of a cell can be deleted using the <class_doc href="Cell#clear_insts"/> method. 
  </p>

  <p>
  An instance can be replaced by another CellInstArray object using the <class_doc href="Cell#replace"/> method. The properties ID can be changed
  using the <class_doc href="Cell#replace_prop_id"/> method. It is easier however to use the Instance object's "cell_inst=" or "prop_id=" method.
  </p>

  <p>
  Instances can be iterated with <class_doc href="Cell#each_inst"/>. <class_doc href="Cell#each_overlapping_inst"/> and <class_doc href="Cell#each_touching_inst"/> delivers all
  instances overlapping or touching a given rectangular region. That means, the instance's overall bounding box overlaps
  or touches the search rectangle.
  </p>

  <p>
  <class_doc href="Cell#each_parent_inst"/> delivers all parent instances. Parent instances are basically reverse instances represented 
  by the <class_doc href="ParentInstArray"/> object. A parent instance identifies are parent cell and 
  the instance of the given cell in that parent cell. This iterator allows deriving all instances of the given cell 
  in other cells.
  </p>

  <p>Instances can be transformed with a given transformation (either a orthogonal or a general complex transformation)
  using the <class_doc href="Cell#transform"/> method. This method invalidates the Instance pointer given as the argument and returns a
  new Instance pointer to the new cell instance.
  </p>

  <p>
  A floating-point integer class exists too (<class_doc href="DCellInstArray"/>). By convention
  this object represent an instance in micrometer units. If such an object is requested from the cell it
  is converted from an integer-type object in database units to a floating-point type object in micrometer units
  by multiplying with the database unit. When sending such an object to the cell the same happens in 
  reverse. Internally, the integer type is used.
  </p>
  
  <h3>Cells, libraries and PCells</h3>

  <p>If a cell is a cell imported from a library, <class_doc href="Cell#is_library_cell?"/> will return true and it is possible to derive
  the Library object from which this cell is imported using the <class_doc href="Cell#library"/> method. <class_doc href="Cell#library_cell_index"/> will 
  return the cell index of the cell in the library's local layout.
  </p>

  <p>If a cell is a PCell variant, either directly from the layout or from a library, <class_doc href="Cell#is_pcell_variant?"/> returns true.
  This method can also be called on an Instance object in which case it delivers true if the instance is an instance of
  a PCell. <class_doc href="Cell#pcell_id"/> returns the PCell declaration ID if the cell is a PCell variant. <class_doc href="Cell#pcell_declaration"/> will
  return the PCell declaration object. There is also a overload of "pcell_declaration" that determines the PCell declaration
  object for an Instance if it is a PCell instance. <class_doc href="Cell#pcell_parameters"/> delivers the PCell parameters for a cell (if it is
  a PCell variant) or an instance (if it is a PCell instance). The PCell parameters are an array of variable-type values
  and the interpretation is dependent on the PCell implementation. The <class_doc href="PCellDeclaration"/> object 
  which can be obtained through "pcell_declaration" gives the necessary information about the interpretation of the 
  parameters.
  </p>

  <p>
  Finally, <class_doc href="Cell#refresh"/> allows refreshing the layout of a proxy cell, i.e. transfer the current state of a library
  cell into this cell or recompute the PCell layout.
  Usually this method needs not to be called. When PCell parameters change for example, the layout is automatically
  recomputed.
  </p>

  <h3>Cells and PCell instances</h3>

  <p>
  A cell can be a PCell variant as we've seen above. In addition, a cell can hold PCell instances.
  The parameters of PCell instances can be modified from the cell using <class_doc href="Cell#change_pcell_parameter"/> for
  individual parameters given by name or <class_doc href="Cell#change_pcell_parameters"/> for all parameters. 
  For changing all parameters it is required to know the parameter's order and meaning. The order can be
  obtained from the PCell declaration class which itself can be retrieved from a PCell instance with <class_doc href="Cell#pcell_declaration"/>
  (with the instance as the first argument).
  </p>

  <p>
  The PCell parameters of a PCell instance can be obtained with <class_doc href="Cell#pcell_parameters"/> (with the 
  instance as the first argument). To get a specific parameter, use the PCell declaration object which lists the
  parameters on the order they are delivered by the "pcell_parameters" method.
  </p>

  <h2>The CellInstArray class</h2>

  <keyword name="CellInstArray"/>
  <p>
  Despite its name, a <class_doc href="CellInstArray"/> object holds a cell reference which is
  not only an array, but also a single instances. The object represents a raw instance, in contrast to the 
  Instance object which is basically a pointer to an instance inside the database. CellInstArray objects as raw instances can be created, 
  copied, modified and stored in the usual containers, but once they are stored inside the Cell object, they can
  be addressed by the Instance object.
  </p>

  <p>
  The CellInstArray object represents either single instances or array instances. Array instances correspond
  to GDS2 AREF records and are regular, two-dimensional (not necessarily orthogonal) arrays of instances.
  A single instance consist of a cell index, denoting the cell that is instantiated and a single transformation,
  which can be either a simple, orthogonal affine transformation without a magnification (a Trans object, see 
  <class_doc href="Trans"/>) or a general affine transformation (a CplxTrans object, see 
  <class_doc href="CplxTrans"/>). A cell instance array in addition specifies two dimensions (na, nb) and shift
  vectors (a, b). For each individual instance of the array, an additional displacement is added to the 
  transformation which is computed by the following formula:
  </p>

  <pre>d=i*a+j*b   (i=0..na-1, j=0..nb-1)</pre>

  <p>
  A CellInstArray object that represents an array will return true on <class_doc href="CellInstArray#is_regular_array?"/>. In that case,
  the <class_doc href="CellInstArray#a"/> and <class_doc href="CellInstArray#b"/> attributes are the basic vectors of the array and <class_doc href="CellInstArray#na"/> and <class_doc href="CellInstArray#nb"/> are 
  the dimensions of the array. <class_doc href="CellInstArray#size"/> is the number of instances in the array.
  </p>

  <p>
  A CellInstArray with a simple transformation will return false on <class_doc href="CellInstArray#is_complex?"/> and the 
  <class_doc href="CellInstArray#trans"/> attributes gives the basic transformation of the instance. If the transformation is complex, 
  i.e. has a rotation angle which is not a multiple of 90 degree or a magnification, <class_doc href="CellInstArray#is_complex?"/>
  will return true and <class_doc href="CellInstArray#cplx_trans"/> should be used instead of <class_doc href="CellInstArray#trans"/>. In any case, <class_doc href="CellInstArray#cplx_trans"/>
  gives the correct transformation.
  </p>

  <p>The <class_doc href="CellInstArray#cell_index"/> attribute gets or sets the cell index. The <class_doc href="CellInstArray#bbox"/> and <class_doc href="CellInstArray#bbox_per_layer"/>
  methods deliver the total bounding box of the instance including all instances for an array. <class_doc href="CellInstArray#bbox_per_layer"/>
  gives the bounding box for a single layer. Since the instance only knows the cell index, these methods require
  a Layout object in order to derive the actual cell's bounding box.
  </p>

  <p>
  A CellInstArray object can be inverted using the <class_doc href="CellInstArray#invert"/> method. This method returns an array which
  represents the ways the parent cell is seen from the child cell. A CellInstArray object can also be transformed
  by a given transformation. The <class_doc href="CellInstArray#transform"/> method will (like <class_doc href="CellInstArray#invert"/>) transform the object in-place,
  i.e. modify the object. <class_doc href="CellInstArray#transformed"/> will do the same, but leave the object it is called on and return
  a modified copy (out-of-place). Various variants of the <class_doc href="CellInstArray#transform"/> and <class_doc href="CellInstArray#transformed"/> methods exist
  taking different forms of transformations (simple, complex).
  </p>

  <p>
  The floating-point variant (<class_doc href="DCellInstArray"/>) behaves the same way, except that by convention the 
  unit of coordinates is micrometers.
  </p>
  
  <h2>The Instance class</h2>

  <keyword name="Instance"/>
  <p>
  As stated earlier, the <class_doc href="Instance"/> object represents a cell instance
  in the database. Technically it acts as a proxy to some CellInstArray inside the database.
  In addition, it provides access to properties attached to the instance. Instance objects play an important
  role in the Cell class to identify a certain instance, for example to delete it.
  </p>

  <p>
  The Instance class provides a couple of methods that give read access to the underlying CellInstArray object
  (<class_doc href="Instance#a"/>, <class_doc href="Instance#b"/>, <class_doc href="Instance#na"/>, <class_doc href="Instance#nb"/>, <class_doc href="Instance#size"/>, <class_doc href="Instance#trans"/>, <class_doc href="Instance#cplx_trans"/>, 
  <class_doc href="Instance#cell_index"/>, <class_doc href="Instance#cell"/>, <class_doc href="Instance#is_complex?"/> or
  <class_doc href="Instance#is_regular_array?"/>). The whole CellInstArray object can be read with the <class_doc href="Instance#cell_inst"/> method.
  It is possible to copy (dup) and modify that object and replace the current CellInstArray with the new 
  one using <class_doc href="Instance#cell_inst="/>. Please note, that this operation may invalidate iterators and should not
  be done inside a loop using "Cell::each_inst" for example.
  </p>

  <p>
  The cell the Instance object lives in can be obtained with <class_doc href="Instance#cell"/>. <class_doc href="Instance#cell_index"/> basically
  renders the same information, but in form of a cell index. The cell can be assigned (<class_doc href="Instance#cell="/>) which changes is to
  refer to a different cell.
  </p>

  <p>
  The layout the instance lives in can be obtained with <class_doc href="Instance#layout"/>. The cell the instance lives in
  is returned by <class_doc href="Instance#parent_cell"/>. The parent cell can be assigned (<class_doc href="Instance#parent_cell="/>), which effectively moves the instance to
  a different cell.
  </p>

  <p>
  User properties can be accessed through the <class_doc href="Instance#prop_id"/> attribute or, more convenient, through the 
  <class_doc href="Instance#property"/>, <class_doc href="Instance#delete_property"/> or <class_doc href="Instance#set_property"/> methods. Please note that changing the
  property ID or the property values may invalidate iterators as well. 
  </p>

  <p>
  An instance has an equality operator. That operator returns true, if the Instances identify the same object.
  </p>
  
  <h2>The Shapes class</h2>

  <keyword name="Shapes"/>
  <p>
  The <class_doc href="Shapes"/> object is the basic container for geometrical shapes. It
  stores geometrical primitives (Boxes, Polygons, Paths, Texts and Edges) either directly or 
  in compressed form to achieve a low memory usage. For example, OASIS shape arrays are stored 
  as compact arrays when KLayout is used in viewer mode. 
  The Shapes container provides a simplified view through the Shape object which is basically
  a pointer to an individual instance of a geometrical primitive. The Shapes container provides
  access to the primitives through Shape objects. 
  </p>

  <p>
  In editable mode (i.e. if a Shapes container lives in an editable Layout object), the 
  shapes can be modified or deleted after they have been inserted. In the opposite mode (viewer mode), shapes can be added, but not
  modified nor deleted. 
  </p>

  <p>
  A Shapes container is usually obtained from a cell with a given layer index and is filled with 
  geometrical primitives using one of the <class_doc href="Shapes#insert"/> methods. Please note that the shapes
  are specified in integer coordinates when you use the integer type objects and micrometer
  units when using the floating-point type objects (whose classes start with "D"):
  </p>

<pre># cell = a Cell object
# layer_index = the index of a the layer
shapes = cell.shapes(layer_index)
shapes.insert(RBA::Box::new(0, 0, 1000, 2000))</pre>

  <p>
  With floating-point objects:
  </p>

<pre># cell = a Cell object
# layer_index = the index of a the layer
shapes = cell.shapes(layer_index)
shapes.insert(RBA::DBox::new(0.0, 0.0, 1.0, 2.0))</pre>

  <p>
  A Shapes object can also be created without a cell:
  </p>

<pre>shapes = RBA::Shapes::new
shapes.insert(RBA::Box::new(0, 0, 1000, 2000))</pre>

  <p>
  Standalone Shapes objects can be useful when the methods of the Shapes object are required
  (for example, region queries through "each_overlapping"). There are are variety of "insert"
  methods available, some of which copy shapes from other Shapes containers using a Shape 
  object as the reference for the source object. Some of these variants allow one to specify a
  transformation which is applied before the shape is inserted. There are also variants
  for all geometrical primitives with or without a properties ID.
  </p>

  <p>
  If a Shapes container is empty, <class_doc href="Shapes#is_empty?"/> will return true. The content of another
  Shapes container can be assigned to a Shapes object with the <class_doc href="Shapes#assign"/> method. The 
  number of geometrical primitives inside the Shapes container can be obtained with the
  <class_doc href="Shapes#size"/> method. All shapes in the Shapes container can be deleted with the <class_doc href="Shapes#clear"/> method.
  </p>

  <p>
  The content of the Shapes container can be iterated with the <class_doc href="Shapes#each"/> iterator. If will
  deliver Shape objects pointing to the current geometrical primitive. The <class_doc href="Shapes#each_overlapping"/>
  and <class_doc href="Shapes#each_touching"/> methods deliver only those primitives whose bounding box overlaps
  or touches the given rectangle. All iterators allow one to specify flags which confine the
  kind of shape delivered. The flags are a combination of the "S..." constants. For example:
  </p>

<pre># delivers all primitives:
shapes.each(RBA::Shapes::SAll) { |s| ... }
# delivers all primitives which have user properties attached:
shapes.each(RBA::Shapes::SAllWithProperties) { |s| ... }
# delivers only texts:
shapes.each(RBA::Shapes::STexts) { |s| ... }
# delivers only polygons and boxes:
shapes.each(RBA::Shapes::SBoxes | RBA::Shapes::SPolygons) { |s| ... }</pre>

  <p>
  A geometrical primitive inside the container can be erased using the <class_doc href="Shapes#erase"/>
  method. It is safe to erase shapes inside an iterator loop for editable containers.
  </p>

  <p>
  Shapes can be replaced by other primitives using one of the <k>replace</k> methods.
  Please note that using "replace" inside an iterator loop may lead to unexpected 
  behavior of the iterator, so modifying a shape inside an iterator loop should be
  avoided. Here is an example:
  </p>

  <pre># DON'T:
# (replace polygons by their bounding boxes)
shapes.each do |shape|
  if shape.is_polygon?
    shapes.replace(shape, shape.bbox)
  end
end

# DO
# (replace polygons by their bounding boxes)
shapes_to_modify = []
shapes.each do |shape|
  if shape.is_polygon?
    shapes_to_modify.push(shape)
  end
end
shapes_to_modify.each do |shape|
  shapes.replace(shape, shape.bbox)
end</pre>

  <p>
  The latter solution requires some more memory but is in general safer.
  It is safe however to replace an object by the same kind of object inside a loop.
  </p>

  <p>
  Shapes can be transformed by using one of the <class_doc href="Shapes#transform"/> methods provided
  by the Shapes object. Variants for simple and complex transformations exist. 
  Please note that using a arbitrary-angle transformation on a box (i.e. a CplxTrans
  object with a rotation angle of 45 degree) will not render a rotated box since a box 
  is by definition parallel to the axes. Instead this operation will render the 
  bounding box of the rotated box.
  Transforming shapes is safe inside an iterator loop.
  </p>

  <p>
  The Shapes container also manages user properties by employing properties ID's. 
  Properties can be modified by obtaining a new ID from the layout object and 
  replacing the property ID using the <class_doc href="Shapes#replace_prop_id"/> method. However it's
  much more convenient to use the <class_doc href="Shape#property"/>, <class_doc href="Shape#set_property"/> or
  <class_doc href="Shape#delete_property"/> methods of the Shape object. In both cases however, 
  modifying the properties should be avoided inside an iterator loop.
  </p>

  <p>
  All shapes inside a shape container can be transformed using <class_doc href="Shapes#transform"/>.
  </p>

  <p>
  With version 0.23, new collection objects entered the stage: <class_doc href="Region"/>, <class_doc href="Edges"/> and
  <class_doc href="EdgePairs"/> which basically provide a way to store polygons, edges or edge pair objects 
  independently from the shapes container. They are mainly used to implement bulk operations, specifically for
  the DRC functionality. The cooperate with the shapes container in the sense that they can be inserted into 
  a shapes container which will produce polygons or edges in the layout database (edge pairs are converted to single
  edges or polygons. These classes are discussed in <link href="/programming/geometry_api.xml"/>.
  </p>

  <h2>The Shape class</h2>

  <keyword name="Shape"/>
  <p>
  The <class_doc href="Shape"/> object provides a unified view to a geometrical primitive inside
  a Shapes container. It also plays an important role for addressing geometrical primitives 
  inside a Shapes container. A Shape object has general methods and specific methods that apply 
  depending on its identity.
  </p>

  <h3>General methods</h3>

  <p>
  The <class_doc href="Shape#bbox"/> method delivers the bounding box of the geometrical primitive addressed by
  the Shape object. Please note that the bounding box of a text only contains the single 
  point of the text's origin, not the text drawing itself. 
  </p>

  <p><class_doc href="Shape#cell"/> delivers the Cell object that shape lives in. The same way, <class_doc href="Shape#layout"/>
  delivers the Layout object and <class_doc href="Shape#shapes"/> the Shapes object.
  </p>

  <p><class_doc href="Shape#property"/>, <class_doc href="Shape#set_property"/> and <class_doc href="Shape#delete_property"/> allow modification of the
  user properties of the geometrical primitive. The same can be achieved somewhat less
  conveniently using a properties
  ID with the <class_doc href="Shape#prop_id"/> attributes' write accessor (<class_doc href="Shape#prop_id="/>). Please note the
  comments in the description of the Shapes object regarding the interaction of these modifying
  operations with iterators. <class_doc href="Shape#has_prop_id?"/> returns true, if the shape has user properties
  attached.
  </p>

  <p>
  <class_doc href="Shape#type"/> returns the type code of the shape addressed by the Shape object. This is 
  a detailed code which distinguishes between different internal representations. It's more
  convenient to use one of the <b>is_...?</b> methods. For example <class_doc href="Shape#is_box?"/> returns true,
  if the geometrical primitive is a box. A note about <class_doc href="Shape#is_polygon?"/> and <class_doc href="Shape#is_simple_polygon?"/>:
  usually it is not required to distinguish between both. "is_polygon?" will also return true for 
  simple polygons, so it is likely to be sufficient to just ask for "is_polygon?".
  <class_doc href="Shape#is_user_object?"/> returns true, if the primitive is a custom object. Such objects are 
  rarely used and not supported by the Ruby API currently.
  </p>

  <p>
  <class_doc href="Shape#area"/> delivers the area of the shape. The area is zero for a text object. 
  <class_doc href="Shape#perimeter"/> delivers the perimeter of the shape. The perimeter is zero for a text object. 
  The Shape object
  provides an equality operator which delivers true if two Shape objects point to the same 
  primitive.
  </p>

  <p>
  It is possible to replace a primitive by another one by using the shape assignment methods, i.e.
  <class_doc href="Shape#box="/>, <class_doc href="Shape#path="/>, <class_doc href="Shape#polygon="/>, <class_doc href="Shape#simple_polygon="/>, <class_doc href="Shape#text="/> and <class_doc href="Shape#edge="/>.
  Using these methods is equivalent to the using "replace" on the containing Shapes objects. Please
  see the notes on using "replace" inside iterators there.
  </p>

  <p>
  Floating-point objects are supported too. For example, <class_doc href="Shape#dbox"/> is equivalent to <class_doc href="Shape#box"/>,
  but delivers the object in micrometer units. <class_doc href="Shape#dbox="/> receives a micrometer-unit object.
  <class_doc href="Shape#box_dp1"/> is equivalent to <class_doc href="Shape#box_p1"/>, but gets the first point of the box in micrometer units.
  </p>

  <p>
  The layer index a shape is on can be obtained with <class_doc href="Shape#layer"/>. 
  A shape can be moved to a different layer by assigning a different layer index with <class_doc href="Shape#layer="/>.
  In that context, layers can also be addressed by layer/datatype or name using a <class_doc href="LayerInfo"/> object.
  The respective methods to address a shape's layer then are <class_doc href="Shape#layer_info"/> and
  <class_doc href="Shape#layer_info="/>.
  </p>

  <p>
  A shape can be transformed using one of the <class_doc href="Shape#transform"/> flavors.
  </p>

  <h3>Methods applying for box shapes</h3>

  <p>A Shape object represents a box if it returns true on <class_doc href="Shape#is_box?"/>. 
  The only specific methods that are provided for box type shapes are the <class_doc href="Shape#box"/>
  getter and <class_doc href="Shape#box="/> setter. <class_doc href="Shape#box_center"/>, 
  <class_doc href="Shape#box_center="/>, <class_doc href="Shape#box_p1"/>, <class_doc href="Shape#box_p1="/>,
  <class_doc href="Shape#box_p2"/> and <class_doc href="Shape#box_p2="/> get or modify individual aspects of the 
  box.
  </p>

  <p>
  For the floating-point equivalents in micrometer units see the <class_doc href="Shape"/>.
  </p>
  
  <h3>Methods applying for polygon and simple polygon shapes</h3>

  <p>A Shape object represents a polygon or simple polygon if it returns true on <class_doc href="Shape#is_polygon?"/>. 
  If the object is a simple polygon, it will also return true on <class_doc href="Shape#is_simple_polygon?"/>.
  A simple polygon is just a polygon that cannot have holes.
  </p>

  <p>In every case, the <class_doc href="Shape#each_edge"/> iterator will deliver all edges (connections between points
  of the polygon). 
  <class_doc href="Shape#each_point_hull"/> will deliver the points of the outer (hull) contour and 
  <class_doc href="Shape#each_point_hole"/> will deliver the points of a specific hole contour. <class_doc href="Shape#holes"/> will deliver
  the number of holes. A simple polygon does not have holes and <class_doc href="Shape#holes"/> always gives zero.
  </p>

  <p>The <class_doc href="Shape#polygon"/> getter delivers a <class_doc href="Polygon"/> object. The same
  way <class_doc href="Shape#simple_polygon"/> delivers a <class_doc href="SimplePolygon"/> object. 
  A polygon with holes is converted in that case to a simple polygon by introducing cut lines to connect
  the holes with the outer contour. 
  </p>

  <p>
  The <class_doc href="Shape#polygon="/> and <class_doc href="Shape#simple_polygon="/> setters will replace the current object by the
  given new one.
  </p>

  <p>
  For the floating-point equivalents in micrometer units see the <class_doc href="Shape"/>.
  </p>
  
  <h3>Methods applying for path shapes</h3>

  <p>A Shape object represents a path if it returns true on <class_doc href="Shape#is_path?"/>.
  The path's width can be obtained through the <class_doc href="Shape#path_width"/> method. The extensions of the
  path ends can be obtained with <class_doc href="Shape#path_bgnext"/> and <class_doc href="Shape#path_endext"/> for the start and end
  extensions. The <class_doc href="Path"/> object can be obtained with the <class_doc href="Shape#path"/> getter.
  For the path width and extensions setters are also provided (<class_doc href="Shape#path_width="/>, 
  <class_doc href="Shape#path_bgnext="/> and <class_doc href="Shape#path_endext="/>).
  </p>

  <p>
  The path length can be obtained with <class_doc href="Shape#path_length"/> and includes the begin and end
  extensions. The round-ended path flag can be obtained with <class_doc href="Shape#round_path?"/> flag
  and set with <class_doc href="Shape#round_path="/>.
  </p>

  <p>
  The points of the path's spine can be iterated with <class_doc href="Shape#each_point"/>. <class_doc href="Shape#polygon"/> can be 
  used to obtain the path's contour.
  </p>

  <p>
  For the floating-point equivalents in micrometer units see the <class_doc href="Shape"/>.
  </p>
  
  <h3>Methods applying for text shapes</h3>

  <p>A Shape object represents a text object if it returns true on <class_doc href="Shape#is_text?"/>.
  The text's text string can be obtained with <class_doc href="Shape#text_string"/>. The text's origin and 
  orientation is encoded in a transformation (a Trans object, see <class_doc href="Trans"/>) 
  which can be obtained with the <class_doc href="Shape#text_trans"/> method. 
  The font code, text size and alignment flags can be obtained with the <class_doc href="Shape#text_font"/>,
  <class_doc href="Shape#text_size"/>, <class_doc href="Shape#text_halign"/> and <class_doc href="Shape#text_valign"/> methods. See the description
  of the <class_doc href="Text"/> object for details about these attributes.
  </p>

  <p>
  The text representation attributes can be set with <class_doc href="Shape#text_font="/>, <class_doc href="Shape#text_size="/>, 
  <class_doc href="Shape#text_halign="/> and <class_doc href="Shape#text_valign="/>.
  <class_doc href="Shape#text_trans="/> will modify the text's transformation.
  </p>

  <p>
  <class_doc href="Shape#text"/> will deliver the Text geometrical primitive and <class_doc href="Shape#text="/> allows replacing the
  shape with the given Text object.
  </p>

  <p>
  For the floating-point equivalents in micrometer units see the <class_doc href="Shape"/>.
  </p>
  
  <h3>Methods applying for edge shapes</h3>

  <p>
  A Shape object represents an edge if it returns true on <class_doc href="Shape#is_edge?"/>.
  Edge objects in general are not well supported in KLayout currently. They can be created and manipulated
  by scripts, but cannot be drawn or modified on the user interface. In GDS2 files, edges
  are represented by zero-width paths which is sometimes breaking the conventions of other tools.
  </p>

  <p>The only specific methods that are provided for edge type shapes are the <class_doc href="Shape#edge"/>
  getter and <class_doc href="Shape#edge="/> setter.
  </p>
  
  <p>
  For the floating-point equivalents in micrometer units see the <class_doc href="Shape"/>.
  </p>
  
</doc>


