<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE language SYSTEM "klayout_doc.dtd">

<doc>

  <title>The Qt Binding</title>
  <keyword name="Qt"/>

  <h2-index/>

  <p>
  Starting with 0.22 comes with a large set of Qt classes available through the Ruby binding
  mechanism. This allows integration of Qt user interfaces with Ruby scripts and to use the 
  Qt API, for example the network or SQL classes. To use the Qt bindings, KLayout must be 
  compiled with Qt binding, i.e.
  </p>

  <pre>build.sh -with-qtbinding ...</pre>

  <p>
  The API provided covers the functionality of a certain Qt version. Currently this is Qt 4.6 and Qt 5.5. 
  The API covers the following Qt 4 and Qt 5 modules:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li>QtCore: the basic Qt API</li>
    <li>QtGui: the user interface widgets and supporting classes</li>
    <li>QtXml: support for XML</li>
    <li>QtXmlPatterns (Qt5): XML schema and queries</li>
    <li>QtSql: database support</li>
    <li>QtNetwork: various network protocols and supporting classes</li>
    <li>QtUiTools: dynamically load designer files (.ui)</li>
    <li>QtMultimedia (Qt5): multimedia support</li>
    <li>QtPrintSupport (Qt5): print support</li>
    <li>QtSvg (Qt5): SVG implementation</li>
  </ul>

  <p>
  This article covers the use of the Qt API and special topics related to that. It is recommended
  to read the article about the Ruby binding (<link href="/programming/ruby_binding.xml"/>) for a deeper 
  understanding of the mapping of the Qt API to Ruby.
  </p>

  <p>
  There is some overlap with the "qtruby" project. This project also makes the Qt API available for 
  Ruby. The approach of "qtruby" is similar. Yet there are some differences, in particular the 
  event feature of KLayout, which allows a convient binding of code blocks to signals.
  </p>

  <h2>A First Sample</h2>

  <p>
  This is a first sample of how to use the Qt API.
  To run that sample, open the Macro Development IDE from the "Macros" menu. Add a new macro with the "+" 
  button in the left top tool bar. Choose "General KLayout Macro" from the "General" group as the template.
  Paste the code above into the macro and run the macro with F5. 
  </p>

  <pre>module MyMacro

  include RBA

  dialog = QDialog::new(Application.instance.main_window)
  dialog.windowTitle = "My Dialog"
  
  layout = QHBoxLayout::new(dialog)
  dialog.setLayout(layout)
  
  button = QPushButton.new(dialog)
  layout.addWidget(button)
  button.text = "Click Me"
  button.clicked do 
    QMessageBox::information(dialog, "Message", "I was clicked!")
  end
  
  dialog.exec

end</pre>

  <p>
  The sample creates a <tt>QDialog</tt> with a layout and a button in it. When the button is clicked, a 
  message box appears. This code demonstrates some features of the Ruby binding of the Qt library.
  For example, the button's text is set with an attribute assignment ("<tt>button.text = ...</tt>") rather
  than a method call ("<tt>button.setText(...)</tt>").
  </p>

  <p>
  A noteworthy feature is the event binding which allows associating code blocks with signals.
  In pure Qt, the "clicked" signal of the button would have to be connected to a slot. This is not
  possible without creating a receiver object. With events, that receiver is created internally and
  a code block can be attached to the signal directly:
  </p>

  <pre>  button.clicked do 
    QMessageBox::information(dialog, "Message", "I was clicked!")
  end</pre>

  <p>
  That binding includes the ability to receive signal arguments through block arguments.
  </p>

  <h2>Binding Details</h2>

  <p>
  Given the rules stated in the general Ruby binding documentation (<link href="/programming/ruby_binding.xml"/>)
  the ruby versions of most methods can be derived readily. There are some exceptions however that 
  we will cover here.
  </p>

  <p>
  First, the C++ to Ruby binding lacks some features that are required for some methods. Those 
  methods cannot be bound. Specifically that concerns:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li>Methods that return or require unsupported containers</li>
    <li>Methods that return or require function pointers</li>
    <li>Methods that return or require pointers to pointers or references to pointers</li>
    <li>Methods that require pointers to pass arrays (i.e. <tt>QPolygon::putPoints</tt>)</li>
    <li>Methods that return or require objects which are not available in Ruby for some reason (i.e. <tt>QGenericArgument</tt> or some template classes like <tt>GenericMatrix</tt>)</li>
    <li>Template members</li>
    <li>Methods which are not available on one of the platforms (i.e. <tt>QPrinter::printerSelectionOption</tt>, which 
        is not available on Windows)</li>
    <li>Some operators, like the cast operators</li>
    <li>Methods that require "char *" arguments which will be manipulated (i.e. <tt>QFile::readLineData</tt>)</li>
    <li>Methods that require C++ resources (i.e FILE arguments)</li>
    <li>Methods for which an alternative exists which cannot be distiguished (i.e. variants acceptings 
        <tt>QByteArray</tt> and <tt>QString</tt> - only the <tt>QString</tt> variant is bound in that case)</li>
    <li>Methods and operators which requires a typed argument as disambiguator (i.e. <tt>operator&gt;&gt;</tt>, where
        the variant is selected by examining the type of the argument. For that case, alternatives exists
        which explicitly state the type in the name, for example "<tt>read_i32</tt>")</li>
  </ul>

  <p>
  Some template types are made available to Ruby. In particular that is valid for some <tt>QPair</tt> specializations.
  For example "<tt>QPair&lt;double, double&gt;</tt>" is available as "<tt>QDoublePair</tt>".
  </p>

  <p>
  The naming of some methods has been aligned to Ruby:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li><tt>isX</tt> is available as <tt>isX?</tt>, i.e. <tt>QAction::isSeparator?</tt></li>
    <li><tt>setX</tt> is available as <tt>x=</tt>, i.e. <tt>QAction::iconText=</tt></li>
  </ul>

  <p>In those cases, the original declaration is still available also.</p>

  <p>
  The inheritance hierarchy of classes is mapped to Ruby in most cases. Sometimes that is not possible. For example, if
  the base class is a template (i.e. <tt>QPolygon</tt>, where the base class is a <tt>QVector&lt;QPoint&gt;</tt>).
  In that case, methods are provided that implement the features from the base class in the derived class.
  </p>

  <p>
  Operators are bound to Ruby operators where that makes sense. For example, for <tt>QPoint</tt> the operators are 
  available as expected ("<tt>==</tt>", "<tt>+</tt>" etc.).
  </p>

  <p>
  "<tt>destroy</tt>" and "<tt>create</tt>" have been renamed to "<tt>qt_destroy</tt>" and "<tt>qt_create</tt>" to avoid name clashes with
  identical methods inherited from the RBA binding. "<tt>destroy</tt>" and "<tt>create</tt>" are standard methods which 
  KLayout's Ruby binding defines for every object exposed to Ruby.
  </p>

  <p>
  When a Qt object is created in Ruby space with a parent, its 
  ownership is passed to the parent. It is safe however to keep a reference to that object, because
  KLayout's Ruby binding employs a special Ruby class internally (a proxy) which keeps track of the lifetime
  of the Qt object. If the parent is destroyed, the Qt object is destroyed as well. The internal Qt object will
  be notified and the reference to the Qt object will be invalidated. As a consequence, the Ruby proxy will
  refuse to execute methods on that object.
  </p>

  <p>
  Destroying a Qt object can be necessary for example to free resources. To perform the equivalent of
  the C++ delete operator, use the "<tt>destroy</tt>" method that comes with every class exposed to Ruby.
  After an object is destroyed, the Ruby part of the binding still persists until all references to
  that object are removed. However, it is no longer possible to call methods on these objects.
  </p>

  <p>
  The Qt binding significantly benefits from the dynamic binding of C++ objects. 
  If a C++ pointer is returned, this pointer often is a pointer to a base class. Behind the pointer
  often is an object of a derived class. C++ allows calling of base class methods on that pointer, but 
  not methods of the derived class - the identity of the object is reduced to the base class.
  </p>

  <p>
  For example, if a method returns a <tt>QWidget</tt> pointer for a <tt>QPushButton</tt>, it is not possible to 
  directly set the buttons text, because the method required for that is not part of the <tt>QWidget</tt>
  interface. In C++ one would dynamic_cast the pointer to <tt>QWidget</tt> and set the text then.
  </p>

  <p>
  The Ruby binding automatically upcasts the pointer to the actual object, so the value returned has the real object's
  identity. In that case, delivering a <tt>QWidget</tt> would render a Ruby object that has a <tt>QPushButton</tt>
  identity and it's possible to set the text immediately. If the object was not a <tt>QPushButton</tt>, an
  error would be issued when an attempt is made to call a <tt>QPushButton</tt> method.
  </p>

  <h3>Enums</h3>

  <p>
  Enum types are available as classes to give them a specific context. Since Ruby does not allow
  declaration of classes within classes, enums declared inside a class must be declared as separate classes outside that class.
  The relationship is indicated by the Enum's class name. For example, <tt>QMessageBox::Icon</tt> (C++) is available
  as the Ruby class <tt>QMessageBox_Icon</tt>. The enum values are defined as constants within that class and the enclosing class. 
  For example <tt>QMessageBox::Critical</tt> which is a value for <tt>QMessageBox::Icon</tt> is available as <tt>QMessageBox_Icon::Critical</tt> and <tt>QMessageBox::Critical</tt>
  in Ruby.
  </p>

  <p>
  Starting with version 0.24, the <tt>QFlags</tt> template is supported as a separate class.
  The name of the class indicates the relationship to the enum class.
  For example, <tt>QFlags&lt;QMessageBox::Icon&gt;</tt> is available as <tt>QMessageBox_QFlags_Icon</tt>.
  Enum classes are derived from their respective flags class, so they can serve to initialize arguments
  expecting flags.
  It's hardly required to operate with the flags classes directly, since they are created automatically
  when joining enum's with the "or" (<tt>|</tt>) operator:
  </p>

  <pre>  QMessageBox::Ok                         # A QMessageBox_StandardButton object
  QMessageBox::Ok | QMessageBox::Cancel   # A QMessageBox_QFlags_StandardButton object</pre>

  <p>
  With these definitions, the following is allowed:
  </p>

  <pre>  QMessageBox::information(parent, title, text, QMessageBox::Ok | QMessageBox::Cancel)
  QMessageBox::information(parent, title, text, QMessageBox::Ok)</pre>

  <h2>Using the designer</h2>

  <p>
  It is possible to load a dialog from a UI designer (.ui) file. Have a look at the following sample:
  </p>

  <pre>module MyMacro
 
  include RBA

  ui_file = QFile::new(QFileInfo::new($0).dir.filePath("MyDialog.ui"))
  ui_file.open(QIODevice::ReadOnly)
  dialog = QUiLoader::new.load(ui_file, Application::instance.main_window)
  ui_file.close
  
  def dialog.setup
    button.clicked do
      slider.value = (slider.value + 1) % 100
    end
  end

  dialog.setup
  dialog.exec

end</pre>

  <p>
  This sample tries to locate a designer file called "<tt>MyDialog.ui</tt>" relative to the 
  macro's path (in <tt>$0</tt>). It uses the <class_doc href="QUiLoader"/> class to load and 
  create the dialog. In that sample, "<tt>MyDialog</tt>" defines a dialog with two widgets: a <tt>QPushButton</tt>
  ("button") and a <tt>QSlider</tt> ("slider").
  Because of the dynamic binding in Ruby, "dialog" will already have the correct class and
  we don't have to cast the pointer delivered by <tt>QUiLoader::load</tt> before we can call "exec".
  </p>

  <p>
  This sample exploits a nice Ruby feature: in Ruby it is possible to dynamically add methods
  to an instance. This allows extending the <tt>QDialog</tt> object we got from <tt>QFormLoader</tt> by custom code.
  In our case we add a "setup" method. This method installs the custom logic of the dialog. 
  It makes use of a convenience feature implemented in <tt>QObject</tt>'s Ruby binding: all named child objects
  of an object are available through accessor methods. Therefore we can access "button" and "slider"
  by their name to install an event handler that updates the slider value each time the button
  is clicked.
  </p>

  <p>
  After calling setup on the dialog we have initialized it and we can show it with "exec".
  </p>

  <h2>Behind The Scenes</h2>

  <p>
  The mechanism behind the Ruby binding a based on the RBA/GSI framework of KLayout. 
  In order to be able to derive from existing classes, that framework needs to add a 
  kind of interfacing class atop of existing classes. Thus, the framework exposes
  every Qt class in two ways:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li>Directly, without the ability to reimplement virtual methods. This is the way,
    existing Qt objects are addressed. The Ruby classes for that case are called "X_Native" where
    "X" is the name of the Qt class (for example, "<tt>QObject_Native</tt>"). When you receive a 
    reference to a Qt object created by C++ code, this reference will have the native class
    type.
    </li>
    <li>Indirectly through an interface class. This is the object created when you instantiate
    a Qt object in Ruby. All virtual methods will be rerouted to the Ruby dispatcher. That allows
    to reimplement every virtual method, but also adds some overhead to every virtual method call.
    The name of these classes is identical to the name of the Qt class. In the swig tool, those
    classes are called "director classes".
    </li>
  </ul>

  <p>
  The difference between the native and interface classes is important if you test the type
  of a object. The difference between both cases is the scope. The native classes will always
  match. The interface classes will only match if the object was created by Ruby code:
  </p>

  <pre>b = dialog.button
# this will not render true, if the button was created by QUiLoader for example
b.is_a?(QPushButton)
# this is correct:
b.is_a?(QPushButton_Native)</pre>

  <p>
  To avoid confusion, the native classes do not appear in the documentation. They would just
  add another level of inheritance without providing additional methods.
  </p>

</doc>
