<!DOCTYPE language SYSTEM "klayout_doc.dtd">

<doc>

  <title>Basic Editor Options</title>
  <keyword name="Editing"/>
  <keyword name="Drawing"/>
  <keyword name="Edit mode"/>

  <p>
  Most tools being using in editing mode have certain options, i.e. 
  when drawing a path, the width and extension mode has to be specified. 
  There exists a general setup dialog for editing options. It can be 
  opened using "Editor Options" from the "Edit" menu or using the F3 
  shortcut (unless overridden).
  </p>

  <p>
  In the dialog there is always a generic settings tab and - depending on 
  the tool chosen - a tool specific tab. On the generic tab, these settings
  can be changed:
  </p>

  <keyword name="Grid"/>
  <keyword name="Angle constraint"/>
  <keyword name="Direction constraint"/>
  <keyword name="Top level mode"/>
  <ul>
    <li><b>Editor grid:</b> Every editing operation is confined to that grid.
      It can be either disabled, aligned with the global grid (used i.e. for rulers and
      display) or specified explicitly. It can even be anisotropic - i.e. there can be 
      a different grid in y than in x direction.
    </li>
    <li><b>Connection angle constraint:</b> When a connection is drawing, i.e. a segment of a path
      or an edge of a polygon, this mode determines, if the segment or edge is confined to 
      certain directions. In "Any Angle" mode, there is no such confinement. In "Diagonal" mode, 
      the edge or segment can be vertical, horizontal or in one of the two diagonal directions. In "Manhattan"
      mode, only horizontal and vertical edges or segments are allowed. 
    </li>
    <li><a name="move_ac"/><b>Movement direction constraint:</b> When something a dragged (i.e. moved), this mode determines
      if the movement is confined to certain directions. In "Any Direction" mode, there is no such
      confinement. In "Diagonal" mode, 
      the movement can be vertical, horizontal or in one of the two diagonal directions. 
      In "Manhattan" mode, only horizontal and vertical movements are allowed. 
    </li>
    <li><b>Top level selection mode:</b> In top level selection mode (when the check box is checked), 
      only elements on the 
      level of the currently shown cell are selected ("top level" refers to the top level of the 
      currently shown cell here). That means, that if shapes from a subcell are selected, the whole
      instance of this subcell is selected.
      <div>
      In hierarchical selection mode (when the check box is not checked), elements are selected from 
      subcells are well. This mode allows in-place editing of subcells which is a powerful feature but 
      also creates strange side effects if other instances of this cell changes as well.
      </div>
    </li>
  </ul>

  <p>
  Whenever you change something in the settings dialog, use "Apply" or "Ok" to apply your changes.
  </p>

</doc>

