<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE language SYSTEM "klayout_doc.dtd">

<doc>

  <title>About Libraries</title>
  <keyword name="Library"/>
  <keyword name="Libraries"/>

  <p>
  Starting with version 0.22, KLayout offers a library concept. 
  Libraries are a way to import cell layout into a layout from the outside and
  thus a convenient way to provide standard building blocks for the layout. 
  Using a cell from a library is easy: when asked for a cell, select
  the library where to take the cell from and choose a cell from that
  library. 
  </p>

  <p>
  Libraries are basically just foreign layouts that are virtually linked
  to the current layout. When a cell is imported from a library, it is 
  copied into the current layout, so that the current layout by itself 
  is a valid entity.
  </p>

  <p>
  When a layout containing library references is saved, KLayout stores
  some meta information in that file which allows it to restore the
  library links and related information.
  For GDS, that meta information is stored in a separate top cell. For OASIS,
  the meta information is stored in special per-cell properties.
  For other formats, the meta information is not stored currently.
  </p>

  <p>
  Libraries can be provided in several ways:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li><p><b>As ordinary layout files:</b> 
      Such libraries are simple layout files (GDS, OASIS or other support format). KLayout looks up
      those libraries in the "libraries" subfolders of the search path and gathers all layout files
      it finds there into the library repository.</p>
      <p>The search path usually includes the installation site (where the KLayout executable resides)
      and the application folder (i.e. "~/.klayout" on Linux). Hence libraries can be installed
      locally (i.e. in "~/.klayout/libraries") or globally (at the installation site). 
      </p>
      <p>
      For GDS files, the library name will be the LIBNAME of the GDS file. Otherwise it will be the
      name of the library file minus the extension.
      </p>
    </li>
    <li><b>Coded libraries:</b>
      Such libraries are provided by code, either through shared objects/DLL's or through Ruby code.
      Basically such code has to provide a layout object containing the library cells. 
      A coded library can also provide PCells (parametrized cells) as library components.
      Sell <link href="/about/about_pcells.xml"/> for details about parametrized cells.
    </li>
  </ul>

  <p>
  Starting with version 0.25, libraries can be provides through packages. This means, they can be downloaded from some
  repository and can be managed within the package manager. Library installation is very simple
  this way. Library deinstallation too. See <link href="/about/packages.xml"/> for details
  about packages.
  </p>

</doc>

