<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE language SYSTEM "klayout_doc.dtd">

<doc>

  <title>The 2.5d View</title>
  <keyword name="2.5d"/>
  <keyword name="3d"/>
  <keyword name="2.5d View"/>
  <keyword name="z-Stack"/>

  <h2-index/>

  <p>
  The "2.5d view" offers a semi-3d view of the layout. It's not a full 3d view as the layers are only extruded vertically
  into layers with a certain thickness. The view cannot model process topology, but it can visualize
  wiring congestions in a three-dimensional space or the vertical relative dimensions of features of the process stack.
  </p>

  <p>
  To open the view, use "Tools/2.5d View". Currently, the performance is limited, a rough number for a
  practical limit is around 100k polygons. The 2.5d view is only available, if KLayout was compiled with
  OpenGL support.
  </p>

  <p>
  <img src="/about/25d_screenshot.png"/>
  </p>

  <h2>Setup</h2>

  <p>
  The 2.5d view needs a technology setup explaining the way the layers are transformed into planes.
  The setup is provided within a technology. Open the technology manager (File/Manage Technologies) and
  navigate to the "Z Stack (2.5d)" component. The setup is basically a list of entries listing the 
  layer from which to take the shapes and the depth information.
  </p>

  <p>
  Each entry is a single line. Empty lines are ignored. Everything after a '#' character is 
  considered a comment.
  </p>

  <p>
  Each specification line consists of a layer specification, a colon and arguments.
  The arguments are named (like "x=...") or in serial. Parameters are separated by comma or blanks.
  Named arguments are:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li> <b>zstart</b>:  The lower z position of the extruded layer in µm </li>
    <li> <b>zstop</b>: The upper z position of the extruded layer in µm </li>
    <li> <b>height</b>:  The height of the extruded layer in µm </li>
  </ul>

  <p>
  'height', 'zstart' and 'zstop' can be used in any combination. If no value is given for 'zstart',
  the upper level of the previous layer will be used.
  </p>

  <p>
  If a single unnamed parameter is given, it corresponds to 'height'. Two parameters correspond to
  'zstart' and 'zstop'.
  </p>

  <p>
  Here are some examples:
  </p>

  <pre>1: 0.5 1.5                    # extrude layer 1/0 from 0.5 to 1.5 vertically\n"
1/0: 0.5 1.5                  # same with explicit datatype\n"
1: zstop=1.5, zstart=0.5      # same with named parameters\n"
1: height=1.0, zstop=1.5      # same with z stop minus height\n"
1: 1.0 zstop=1.5              # same with height as unnamed parameter\n"
  </pre>

  <h4>Variables</h4>

  <p>
  You can declare variables inside the setup files and use them in formulas for
  computed values. Variables are defined and set with the "var" keyword on a single line.
  The notation follows the "expression" syntax used in many other places inside KLayout
  (<link href="/about/expressions.xml"/>).
  </p>

  <p>
  Here is an example:
  </p>

  <pre>var hmetal = 0.48\n"
7/0: 0.5 0.5+hmetal*2        # 2x thick metal\n"
</pre>

  <h4>Conditionals</h4>

  <p>
  For more flexibility, but of little practical use for now, conditionals are provided.
  "if", "else", "elsif" and "end" for as in other languages, e.g. Ruby:
  </p>

  <pre>var thick_m1 = true
if thickm1
  1: 0.5 1.5
else
  1: 0.5 1.2
end
</pre>

  <h2>Navigating the 2.5d View</h2>
  <keyword>navigation</keyword>
  <keyword>2.5d navigation</keyword>

  <p>
  The navigation is based on the movement of the camera while the scene is 
  formed by the extruded layout. The scene can be scaled to provide zoom features.
  Scaling and rotation is relative to the pivot point which is indicated by the 
  compass icon on the ground plane.
  </p>

  <p>
  This is a short list of the navigation controls which act on the camera:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li> Dragging with the right mouse button down: change azimuth and elevation angle </li>
    <li> Dragging with the middle mouse button down: move the pivot up and down or left and right </li>
    <li> Mouse wheel: moves the pivot forward and backward </li>
    <li> Control key + mouse wheel: magnify or shrink the layout </li>
    <li> Press and hold shift key: switch to top level view (see below) </li>
    <li> Up/down keys: move the pivot forward or backward </li>
    <li> Left/right keys: move the pivot to the left or the right </li>
    <li> Control + up/down keys: change the elevation angle </li>
    <li> Control + left/right keys: change the azimuth angle </li>
  </ul>

  <p>
  In top level view, the navigation is slightly different:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li> Dragging with the right mouse button down: change azimuth angle </li>
    <li> mouse wheel: magnify or shrink the layout </li>
    <li> Up/down/left/right keys: move the pivot on the horizontal plane </li>
  </ul>

</doc>

