<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE language SYSTEM "klayout_doc.dtd">

<doc>

  <title>Coding PCells In Ruby</title>
  <keyword name="Ruby"/>
  <keyword name="PCell"/>
  <keyword name="Programming"/>
  <keyword name="RBA"/>

  <h2-index/>

  <p>
  A good starting point for Ruby PCells is the PCell sample. Create a macro in the
  macro development IDE (use the "+" button) and choose "PCell sample" from the 
  templates.
  </p>

  <h2>The Sample</h2>

  <p>
  We'll do a code walk through that sample here and explain the concepts while 
  doing so.
  Here is the complete sample:
  </p>

  <pre># Sample PCell
#
# This sample PCell implements a library called "MyLib" with a single PCell that
# draws a circle. It demonstrates the basic implementation techniques for a PCell 
# and how to use the "guiding shape" feature to implement a handle for the circle
# radius.
# 
# NOTE: after changing the code, the macro needs to be rerun to install the new
# implementation. The macro is also set to "auto run" to install the PCell 
# when KLayout is run.

module MyLib

  include RBA

  # Remove any definition of our classes (this helps when 
  # reexecuting this code after a change has been applied)
  MyLib.constants.member?(:Circle) &amp;&amp; remove_const(:Circle)
  MyLib.constants.member?(:MyLib) &amp;&amp; remove_const(:MyLib)
  
  # The PCell declaration for the circle
  class Circle &lt; PCellDeclarationHelper
  
    include RBA

    def initialize

      # Important: initialize the super class
      super

      # declare the parameters
      param(:l, TypeLayer, "Layer", :default =&gt; LayerInfo::new(1, 0))
      param(:s, TypeShape, "", :default =&gt; DPoint::new(0, 0))
      param(:r, TypeDouble, "Radius", :default =&gt; 0.1)
      param(:n, TypeInt, "Number of points", :default =&gt; 64)     
      # this hidden parameter is used to determine whether the radius has changed
      # or the "s" handle has been moved
      param(:ru, TypeDouble, "Radius", :default =&gt; 0.0, :hidden =&gt; true)

    end
  
    def display_text_impl
      # Provide a descriptive text for the cell
      "Circle(L=#{l.to_s},R=#{'%.3f' % r.to_f})"
    end
    
    def coerce_parameters_impl
    
      # We employ coerce_parameters_impl to decide whether the handle or the 
      # numeric parameter has changed (by comparing against the effective 
      # radius ru) and set ru to the effective radius. We also update the 
      # numerical value or the shape, depending on which on has not changed.
      rs = nil
      if s.is_a?(DPoint) 
        # compute distance in micron
        rs = s.distance(DPoint::new(0, 0))
      end 
      if rs &amp;&amp; (r-ru).abs &lt; 1e-6
        set_ru rs
        set_r rs 
      else
        set_ru r 
        set_s DPoint::new(-r, 0)
      end
      
      # n must be larger or equal than 4
      n &gt; 4 || (set_n 4)
       
    end
    
    def can_create_from_shape_impl
      # Implement the "Create PCell from shape" protocol: we can use any shape which 
      # has a finite bounding box
      shape.is_box? || shape.is_polygon? || shape.is_path?
    end
    
    def parameters_from_shape_impl
      # Implement the "Create PCell from shape" protocol: we set r and l from the shape's 
      # bounding box width and layer
      set_r shape.bbox.width * layout.dbu / 2
      set_l layout.get_info(layer)
    end
    
    def transformation_from_shape_impl
      # Implement the "Create PCell from shape" protocol: we use the center of the shape's
      # bounding box to determine the transformation
      Trans.new(shape.bbox.center)
    end
    
    def produce_impl
    
      # This is the main part of the implementation: create the layout

      # fetch the parameters
      ru_dbu = ru / layout.dbu
      
      # compute the circle
      pts = []
      da = Math::PI * 2 / n
      n.times do |i|
        pts.push(Point.from_dpoint(DPoint.new(ru_dbu * Math::cos(i * da), ru_dbu * Math::sin(i * da))))
      end
      
      # create the shape
      cell.shapes(l_layer).insert(Polygon.new(pts))
      
    end
  
  end
  
  # The library where we will put the PCell into 
  class MyLib &lt; Library
  
    def initialize  
    
      # Set the description
      self.description = "My First Library"
      
      # Create the PCell declarations
      layout.register_pcell("Circle", Circle::new)
      # That would be the place to put in more PCells ...
      
      # Register us with the name "MyLib".
      # If a library with that name already existed, it will be replaced then.
      register("MyLib")
      
    end
  
  end
  
  # Instantiate and register the library
  MyLib::new
  
end</pre>

  <h2>Preamble</h2>

  <p>The first important concepts are PCell class and library. A PCell is provided by implementing a 
  certain class and providing the functionality of the PCell through various methods. In fact there are 
  only three methods which must be implemented. In the sample we use <class_doc href="PCellDeclarationHelper"/> as the 
  base class for our PCell. This is a convenience wrapper around the basic interface, <class_doc href="PCellDeclaration"/>.
  Since that interface is too much "C++"-like and is somewhat tedious to use, the PCellDeclarationHelper
  is the recommended starting point.
  </p>

  <p>Using the same concept, a library is an object derived from the <class_doc href="Library"/> class. It is basically
  a container for PCells and static layout cells. A library has to be initialized (most conveniently in
  the constructor), registered and initialized once. That makes the library available to the system and
  it can be used in layouts.
  </p>

  <p>
  Please note, that the sample PCell is configured for auto-run. This way, the library is installed
  when KLayout starts and before any layouts are loaded. That way, the library is available for 
  layouts read from the command-line for example.
  </p>

  <p>
  Let's now start with our code walk:
  </p>

  <pre>module MyLib

  include RBA

  # Remove any definition of our classes (this helps when 
  # reexecuting this code after a change has been applied)
  MyLib.constants.member?(:Circle) &amp;&amp; remove_const(:Circle)
  MyLib.constants.member?(:MyLib) &amp;&amp; remove_const(:MyLib)</pre>

  <p>
  It is recommended to put the library code into a separate module. That allows 
  mixing in other modules (in that case RBA) without affecting the main module. 
  The second recommendation is to remove classes which are already defined
  with the names we are going to create. While developing a PCell is it necessary to
  frequently rerun the script to register the new version of the library and PCell.
  If we do not remove the existing class, Ruby will refuse to reopen a class
  for example if we change the super class or methods we have deleted will still 
  remain. That is avoided by removing the classes before the create them again. In 
  Ruby, a class can be removed by removing the constant with the class name. Note
  the way, the script checks whether a class is defined by using "member?" on the
  list of constants. This method should be preferred over "const_defined?" which 
  behaves differently on Ruby 1.8 and Ruby 1.9.
  </p>

  <h2>The PCell Class</h2>

  <p>First we define a PCell class derived from <class_doc href="PCellDeclarationHelper"/>. This
  is the most convenient way to declare a PCell:
  </p>

  <pre>  # The PCell declaration for the circle
  class Circle &lt; PCellDeclarationHelper
  
    include RBA</pre>
 
  <p>
  Again we include RBA which allows us to use RBA classes inside the PCell without
  having to write "RBA::" in front of the class names.
  </p>
  
  <p>The initialization of the object is already a very important step. First, it 
  must initialize the super class. Then it has to declare the PCell parameters.
  Each PCell has a set of parameters that define the appearance of the PCell.
  Parameters have a symbolic name, a type, a description and optionally a default
  value and further attributes. The name is important because it identifies the
  parameter throughout the system and in layout files as well. It should not be 
  changed. The description is an arbitrary string and can be changed or localized.
  </p>

  <p>
  Parameters are declared using the "param" method of <class_doc href="PCellDeclarationHelper"/>:
  </p>

  <pre>    def initialize

      # Important: initialize the super class
      super

      # declare the parameters
      param(:l, TypeLayer, "Layer", :default =&gt; LayerInfo::new(1, 0))
      param(:s, TypeShape, "", :default =&gt; DPoint::new(0, 0))
      param(:r, TypeDouble, "Radius", :default =&gt; 0.1)
      param(:n, TypeInt, "Number of points", :default =&gt; 64)     
      # this hidden parameter is used to determine whether the radius has changed
      # or the "s" handle has been moved
      param(:ru, TypeDouble, "Radius", :default =&gt; 0.0, :hidden =&gt; true)

    end</pre>

  <p>
  In that sample we declared a PCell parameter "l" with type "TypeLayer" which indicates that this is 
  a layer in the layout. "s" is a parameter shape represents the handle and is a shape. A shape
  is either of type <class_doc href="DBox"/>, <class_doc href="DText"/>, <class_doc href="DPath"/>, <class_doc href="DPolygon"/> or <class_doc href="DPoint"/>. Shape parameters
  implement the "guiding shape feature" that KLayout offers to manipulate that parameter graphically.
  "r" and "n" are simple numerical parameters. All parameters have default values which are set
  with the "default" symbolic parameter. As a layer, "l" must have a <class_doc href="LayerInfo"/> value.
  "s" is a <class_doc href="DPoint"/> which reflects the handle. Since default values not only preset the parameters
  to a reasonable value but also define the subtype of a parameter (here the <class_doc href="DPoint"/> shape), providing
  a default is strongly recommended. As shapes need to be independent from the database unit for portability, they are expressed in
  micron units. Hence the use of the "D" forms (DPoint etc.).
  </p>

  <p>"ru" is a special parameter. Because we have two ways to modify the radius (the handle and the numerical value), 
  it is used as a shadow parameter do determine which one of these two values has changed. Depending on that
  information, either the handle or the radius is updated. Because this parameter should not be shown in the
  parameter page, it is marked "hidden". 
  </p>

  <p>
  There are some more options for parameters. See the documentation of <class_doc href="PCellDeclarationHelper"/> for 
  more details about the further attributes.
  </p>

  <p>
  The parameter declaration will create accessor methods for each parameter. These accessor methods can be
  used to get and set the current value of the parameter inside the production method and other methods.
  For that, it will use the symbolic name of the parameter. The setter is called "set_x" (where x is the parameter
  name). Although Ruby would allow using "x=" to mimic an assignment, this option leads to some confusion
  with definition of local variables and was not considered here. The following methods are created in the sample:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li><tt>l, set_l, l_layer</tt>: getter and setter for the current value of "l". l_layer is the layer index in the context 
      of the PCell production method. The layer index can be used to access the layer in the layout or cell.</li>
    <li><tt>s, set_s</tt>: getter and setter for the current value of "s".</li>
    <li><tt>r, set_r, n, set_n, ru, set_ru</tt>: same for "r", "n" and "ru".</li>
  </ul>  

  <p>
  After the PCell initialization is finished, we can start with the production code. These are the methods
  that KLayout will call on certain opportunities. The first method that a PCell must implement is the 
  display text callback:
  </p>

  <pre>    def display_text_impl
      # Provide a descriptive text for the cell
      "Circle(L=#{l.to_s},R=#{'%.3f' % r.to_f})"
    end</pre>

  <p>
  KLayout will call this method to fetch a formatted string that represents the content of a PCell. This text
  is used for the cell tree and cell box labels. To avoid confusion, it should start with the name of the
  PCell. The bracket notation is not mandatory, but it's always a good idea to follow some common style.
  The information delivered by this method should be short but contain enough information so that a 
  PCell variant can be distinguished from its sibling. 
  </p>

  <p>
  The next method is called whenever something on the parameters has changed. This method allows
  to adjust the parameters so that they obey certain limitations. It can also raise exceptions for
  invalid parameter combinations. In our case we use this method to adjust the handle or the 
  numeric radius to the effective value. We also enforce a minimum number of vertex counts for the 
  resulting polygon. Implementing this method in general is optional. By default, no modification 
  of the parameters is done:
  </p>
    
  <pre>    def coerce_parameters_impl
    
      # We employ coerce_parameters_impl to decide whether the handle or the 
      # numeric parameter has changed (by comparing against the effective 
      # radius ru) and set ru to the effective radius. We also update the 
      # numerical value or the shape, depending on which on has not changed.
      rs = nil
      if s.is_a?(DPoint) 
        # compute distance in micron
        rs = s.distance(DPoint::new(0, 0))
      end 
      if rs &amp;&amp; (r-ru).abs &lt; 1e-6
        set_ru rs
        set_r rs 
      else
        set_ru r 
        set_s DPoint::new(-r, 0)
      end
      
      # n must be larger or equal than 4
      n &gt; 4 || (set_n 4)
       
    end</pre>
    
  <p>
  The implementation of the following three methods is optional: they are used to 
  implement the "PCell from shape" protocol. If "Create PCell from shape" is selected
  in KLayout's Edit menu, it will call "can_create_from_shape_impl" for each known 
  PCell. This method will be given the shape, layout and layer. If this method responds
  with "true", KLayout offers this PCell as a conversion target in the list. When this
  PCell has been selected, KLayout calls "parameters_from_shape_impl" and "transformation_from_shape_impl"
  to obtain the initial parameters and the initial transformation for the new PCell created
  from that shape. "parameter_from_shape_impl" will use the default values for all parameters
  unless they are set with the respective setters in the implementation body.
  </p>

  <pre>    def can_create_from_shape_impl
      # Implement the "Create PCell from shape" protocol: we can use any shape which 
      # has a finite bounding box
      shape.is_box? || shape.is_polygon? || shape.is_path?
    end

    def parameters_from_shape_impl
      # Implement the "Create PCell from shape" protocol: we set r and l from the shape's 
      # bounding box width and layer
      set_r shape.bbox.width * layout.dbu / 2
      set_l layout.get_info(layer)
    end
    
    def transformation_from_shape_impl
      # Implement the "Create PCell from shape" protocol: we use the center of the shape's
      # bounding box to determine the transformation
      Trans.new(shape.bbox.center)
    end</pre>
    
  <p>
  The most important method is "produce_impl" which actually creates the layout.
  For that, it can use all methods of <class_doc href="Layout"/> and <class_doc href="Cell"/> and most other RBA classes.
  It can even create 
  instances. Although that is possible, it is not recommended to create cells in the 
  production code. This would pretty much degrade performance and lead to a confusing
  variety of cells. It is possible to use boolean operations by using the methods
  of <class_doc href="EdgeProcessor"/> for example. Some care must be taken to avoid interaction with 
  the user interface, in particular calling methods of <class_doc href="LayoutView"/> and <class_doc href="MainWindow"/>
  should be avoided.
  </p>

  <p>
  The actual layout of the PCell is cached and the production code is called only
  when the PCell parameters have changed. However, to reduce the risk of performance 
  degradation, the method should run quickly and not spend too much time in 
  long loops or huge data sets.
  </p>

  <pre>    def produce_impl
    
      # This is the main part of the implementation: create the layout

      # fetch the parameters
      ru_dbu = ru / layout.dbu
      
      # compute the circle
      pts = []
      da = Math::PI * 2 / n
      n.times do |i|
        pts.push(Point.from_dpoint(DPoint.new(ru_dbu * Math::cos(i * da), ru_dbu * Math::sin(i * da))))
      end
      
      # create the shape
      cell.shapes(l_layer).insert(Polygon.new(pts))
      
    end
  
  end
</pre>

  <p>
  Of course, more than one PCell class can be declared. Each PCell type must 
  have an own implementation class which we will use later to create the PCells from.
  </p>

  <h2>The Library</h2>

  <p>
  The library is the container for the PCells.
  All important code is packed into the constructor of the library.
  </p>

  <pre>  # The library where we will put the PCell into 
  class MyLib &lt; Library
  
    def initialize  
    
      # Set the description
      self.description = "My First Library"
      
      # Create the PCell declarations
      layout.register_pcell("Circle", Circle::new)
      # That would be the place to put in more PCells ...
      
      # Register us with the name "MyLib".
      # If a library with that name already existed, it will be replaced then.
      register("MyLib")
      
    end
  
  end</pre>

  <p>
  First, a library needs a description that we set with the description setter. Then, we 
  instantiate all PCell classes once and register that instance in the library space. 
  </p>

  <p>
  The library is basically an ordinary <class_doc href="Layout"/> object that we can access through the 
  "layout" method. The library can consist of more that PCells - all cells that we put into
  the layout will become available as library components (more precisely: all top cells).
  We could use RBA::Layout::read for example to feed the layout with cells from a file.
  </p>

  <p>At the end of the constructor we register our instance inside the system with the 
  given name. To avoid confusion, it is recommended to use the same name for the class
  and the library.
  </p>

  <p>
  Finally we only need to instantiate the library:
  </p>
  
  <pre>  # Instantiate and register the library
  MyLib::new</pre>

  <p>
  This line of code will instantiate the library and, through the constructor, instantiate
  the PCells and register the library. We are done now and can use the library and our PCell.
  </p>

  <h2>Debugging The Code</h2>

  <p>
  When you have modified the code, you need to rerun the script. That will create the classes
  again and re-register the PCells and the Library with the new implementation. PCells already
  living in the layout will be migrated to the new implementation by mapping their parameters by
  their symbolic names.
  </p>

  <p>
  The PCell code can be debugged with KLayout's built-in Ruby debugger. If the macro development
  IDE window is open, just load the PCell code and set a breakpoint. When KLayout calls the 
  PCell implementation, the breakpoint will be triggered. Local variables can be inspected and modified in
  the console for example. Single-stepping is supported as well. If the execution is stopped, KLayout
  will finish the operation with some error message.
  </p>

  <p>
  It is also possible to print output to the console if the macro development IDE is open. Just use
  the methods of stdout that Ruby offers or simply "puts".
  </p>

  <p>
  Please note that while the macro development IDE is opened, macro execution is considerably slower 
  than usually, because the IDE will plug itself into the Ruby interpreter and trace the execution.
  When the IDE window is closed, Ruby runs at full speed. While in a breakpoint, KLayout's main window
  is only half alive. Only the IDE is active and the main window will not even repaint correctly. 
  This prevents possible interactions with the executed code.
  </p>
  
</doc>

